翻译:lalalain
校对:lalalain
有任何问题和建议，请发送E-mail至
lalalain@163.com
或者访问Https://www.cmule.com的同志文艺片板块。
Tommy，来吧，奏起来。
-可以和我跳支舞吗？
-为什么不呢？
男孩就是男孩，理应如此。
你知道，并不是所有的女孩
都会成为个狂躁又嗜血的女同性恋的。
在世间诸般灾祸中，
对于这一不幸我恰恰能够深刻地领会。
她抱怨说，我想你的时间要比想她更多
但这确实是事实，不是吗？
我们先不要讨论这个。
就当我不在好了，你们自便，别拘束。
-但你是个男人，不是个女人啊，
为什么一个男人要娶另一个男人呢？
-为了安全感。
我猜想，总有一天，
你会找着个好女孩，然后安定下来。
是啊，你也有天会找着个好女孩，然后安定下来的。
这些不是我的衣服。
问题是为什么你穿着这衣服。
我只是忽然间变“同志”了！
[片名]：
赛璐璐胶片“衣柜”
----电影中的同性恋
在电影出现以来的100年间，
同性恋们几乎不会在屏幕中出现。
而一旦他们出现了，他们的形象又是供人嘲笑的，
让人怜悯的，
甚至是令人恐惧的。
这些形象也许只是在电影中一闪而过，
但它们仍然是引人注目的，
它们确实留下了巨大的遗产。
而好莱坞,是最大的迷思（myth)创造者。
电影为异性恋者，
创造了一整套关于同性恋者的公众意见，
同时也为同性恋者，
创造了一整套观念，关于如何看待自身。
没有人能够完全逃脱这一影响。
Tony Curtis
(老牌演员，名作有30年代的《热情如火》）：
“电影是我生命的一部分，
也许是所有人生命的一部分，
我们甚至是从电影中学习人生的。
让Cary Grant
(30-60年代著名影星，
代表作《捉贼记》、《西北偏北》等）
教会我们与女士相处时如何表现得体，
如何穿戴整齐，出席晚宴。”
Armistead Maupin
（同性恋作家，撰有《Tales of the City》）：
电影讲述了人们的生活，电影构造了人们的生活
它向我们展示了什么是荣耀的，
什么是悲剧性的，
什么是棒透了的，有趣的，
它展示了每个人都经历的事，每天的日常生活。
但你是个同性恋时，
你却无法在电影中找到这种对你生活的反映，
你这才感到，有什么地方出了差错。”
Susie Bright
（女同性恋作家，创办女性主义色情杂志）：
“你发现自己象个隐身人，象个幽灵。
没人相信这个幽灵是真正存在的。
你感到某种孤立感。”
Whoopi Goldberg
(著名黑人女演员，多次出演同性恋角色）:
来参加这个俱乐部吧。你必须知道有着这样一个群体，
这样一个隐蔽着的群体。
Jan Oxenberg(电影编剧，女同性恋）：
“我们是这么可悲地渴求着关于我们自身的形象，
以至于会有朋友打来电话，
告诉我们‘这部电影你一定要看看’
顺便说一句，这是我的真事，
‘你一定要看，这是部讲“女同志”的电影
里面有很棒的亲密的镜头...好吧，她们是吸血鬼。’
‘不过你还是要去看看，真的很棒。’”
Harvey Fierstein
(著名同性恋编剧，演员，作品有《火炬三部曲》等）
我们对艺术的需要有很多原因，
其中最重要的也许就是将之作为一面镜子，
反射出我们的生活，我们的存在。
在少年时期，我拼命在各类作品中寻找同性恋形象，
只是想摆脱孤单的感觉。
[爱迪生的实验电影 1895年]
Quentin Crisp
(英国著名同性恋作家）：
“我的母亲带我去看无声电影，
她大概是想显示她的谨慎，
她告诉我，这和现实生活毫不相似，不要相信。
她错了，
那些从英伦岛去往美国，
最后又回来的那些人都说着同样一件事：
‘美国就象是你曾梦想过的那部最好的电影’，
确实是这样。”
[《佛罗里达的魔力》 1914年电影]
在电影刚诞生不久时，电影通常将同性恋
作为一种理所当然的幽默资源。
[《矿工艾吉》 1912年电影]
[《土包子》 1923年电影]
richard dyer
（文化研究学者，电影史学者）
”关于‘我是谁’这一问题的想法，
并不完全来自于你自身，也部分来自于你所处的文化。
对于美国文化，又特别来自于电影。
我们从电影中学习怎样成为一个男人，或者女人，
学习关于性的事情。”
[《西部流浪者》 1927年电影]
“店员Clarence
----在一个男人象个男人的国度里，
也会出这样的差错。”
电影确实提供了我们某种历史
关于这个社会是如何看待同性恋的。
“今晚愿意和男孩一起出去玩玩吗？”
“一个非常好的例子是
卓别林的电影《荧幕之后》
[1916年电影 《荧幕之后》]
有一幕是卓别林亲吻了一个看上去象男孩的女孩，
他也知道那是个女孩。
这时另一个人走了过来，目击了这幕，
立刻故意地做出一副娘娘腔的样子，四处摇摆。”
“奇妙的地方是，
这一场景展示了关于同性恋的一些固定的看法。
展示了主流电影完全确信，
观众们能够理解，
这些滑稽的娘娘腔的摇摆是什么意思。”
-Ernest 先生
-Ernest。
亲爱的Ernest!
[1933年电影 《位居我们之上的人们》]
亲爱的Grayston女士。
Ernest,我是多么高兴你能光临此地。
很抱歉我就这么穿着外衣过来，
但你的司机说时间紧迫，于是我就直接来拜访您了。
娘娘腔登场。
同性恋在好莱坞最早的定型角色。
[《柳暗花明》 1934年电影]
娘娘腔的男子似乎占据了一个中间位置，
男人觉得他们女性化，
女人觉得和他们比起来，还是自己更有女人味。
他似乎没有任何性征，
因此他的形象得以在好莱坞走俏。
于是我们看到了这些娘娘腔，
他们不需要被特别说明是同性恋。
人们普遍接受这一点。
Jay Presson Allen
(编剧，撰有《酒店》电影版剧本等）：
“人们潜意识地把娘娘腔等同于同性恋。
关于这个问题人们常常避而不谈。
人们会私下这样谈论，但肯定不会公开地说。”
“尽管这从未被大张旗鼓地讨论过，
但你就是能感觉到。
他们是这样一群小男人，
这些小小瘦瘦的白人男子，
留着小胡子，翘着兰花指。”
慢点，慢点，女孩们，
这些是我的帽子，小心点。
[《百老汇之歌》 1929年电影]
-马上就要上台了。
-我才不管。就是不能让你们弄坏它们。
我早就告诉过你，它们太大了。
听着，女士。
我是为演出设计戏服，不是为剧院设计大门。
我知道，如果你设计大门的话，
一定会镶满薰衣草花边的。
-这里弄破了，昨晚在哪儿快活了？
-Stangler Lewis哪儿。
[《迈特和玛吉》 1934年电影]
今朝有酒今朝醉，恩？
我和你说，如果我们能够让这出戏顺利，
或者至少来得及把珠宝都镶在长筒袜上，
我就可以付清我那件和服的钱了。
Calrence,把这放到箱子里。
不要偷偷地穿。
真小气。
Arthur Laurents
(《西区故事》剧作者，《鸟笼》导演）：
“这是些无聊的陈词滥调，
我并不关心它们是不是射影同性恋的。
我只是觉得这些嘲笑让人反感，
一点也不有趣，空洞无物，
我一直不明白为什么观众们觉得这好笑。
我觉得这就好象嘲笑
Steppin Fetchit（第一位黑人电影演员）
长了一副黑脸孔。”
“我倒有点喜欢娘娘腔，
它确实常常起到消极的作用，
引起人们的嘲笑
但我的观点一直是，
只要同性恋的事情被开诚布公，总有好的一面。
我情愿人们得到这些消极的印象，
也不愿意人们忽视它的存在，
这只是我个人的观点，
考虑到我本人就是个娘娘腔。”
“上上下下，跑遍山丘。”
在另一部电影中，你甚至可以看到娘娘腔
周旋于餐桌之间。
这也是好莱坞最早的对同姓恋酒吧好奇的打量。
[《野女人》 1932年电影]
“一旦遇到个穿着睡裤的水手
我将会因此而辗转难安。”
“登上你日思夜想的那艘战舰啊。”
“象个女仆那样工作。”
“电影中的娘娘腔，总是被当作笑话来看。
似乎变为一个女人是最罪恶不过的事了。
当男人穿着女装，人们就会大笑。
当女人穿着男装，却没有人会笑。
人们只会觉得她看上去棒极了。”
[《摩洛哥》 1930年电影]
“当我还是个青少年的时候，我看到了
Marlene Deitrich出现在电影《摩洛哥》中。
我只是这么随意地调着频道，然后看到她，
从此以后我就开始对老电影着迷起来。
有一幕是她来到一家夜店，穿着这件男式礼服，
让人眩晕。”
“我可以拿走吗？”
“当然。”
“摄影机轻轻地游移，
而我并不是在屏幕的某个角落目睹这幕，
而是在屏幕正中央。
她在这部电影中和 Gary Cooper有一段罗曼史...
但我根本不把这放在眼里。
我只是不停地问自己：‘这个女人是谁？’
‘刚才发生了什么？’
我甚至擅自写了一个剧本，
描述‘事情的真相’。”
“这幕对任何性别的任何人都一样震撼。
很奇怪的是，我不认为人们从此以后，
拍出过被它更性感的东西来了。
人们并不伪装自己的感受，
她确实既让男人兴奋，又让女人动情，
如同事实上应该发生的一样，她吸引了所有人。
如此自由。”
-Ebba
-进来。
[《克丽丝汀女王》 1933年电影]
别冗礼了，你已经忙了一整天了。
早安，Ebba。
-你怎么起得这么早？
-我睡不着。
《克丽丝汀女王》是根据的真人真事改编的，
讲述一个瑞典女王，
同时是个女同性恋。
好莱坞改动了故事，
但是在镜头中我们仍然能找到些蛛丝马迹。
“有这么个传闻，陛下正准备一场与异国的婚礼？”
“完全在胡说。”
“但是，陛下，再这样下去，
你会象一个老女仆那样孤独死去的。”
“我不会那样的，就算孤独的死去，
我也会象个单身汉那样。”
“我们不希望因为某些电影院
播放的某些令人不快的影片，
而让所有的电影院关闭。
[Gustav Ketterer 女士，妇女俱乐部联盟]
对大众开放的电影院应该是更健康的，更合宜的。
[《泰山和他的伙伴》 1934年电影 被审查删去的镜头]
“这些镜头在20、30年代当然算是十分淫秽的，
它们遭到了天主教教会和原教旨主义者的强烈反对。
（原教旨主义：19，20世纪在美国兴起的教派，
强调尊奉圣经原文，反对基督教与现代科学、哲学
以及社会观念妥协）
那时有很多布道坛，鼓吹着原教旨主义的思想，
反对电影屏幕展现的场景。”
[《杀人罪》 1922年电影]
终于，电影巨头们聚集在一起，
作出了一个重大的决定。
Gore Vidal：(美国著名老作家，
受05年诺贝尔文学奖提名，是同性恋者）
“他们说‘让我们来拯救好莱坞吧，
我们需要一个在电影业外的旁观者，’
让政客来担任这角色最适合不过的，
这些人是不可被质疑的。
于是他们调查了当时在任的哈定总统的内阁，
那时，他的内阁成员中有许多人有些未被指控的罪行，
他们最终选择了印地安那州的威尔・海斯前将军，
不得不提的是，他确实长得象米老鼠。
Will Hays[“海斯法典”的头领]：
“这一法典表达了对电影表演的高标准严要求，
它陈述了，作为一种全球化的娱乐事业，
什么样的品味，什么样的公共价值，
才是需要在电影中被表达的。”
Will Hay
带领了电影业最早的自发性的自我审查制度，
最早的运动只是个象征性的，不怎么被认真对待。
但到了1934年，天主教教会
提出了它们的一份计划，
[A级：可接受的；B级：不健康的；C级：遭天谴的]
那时的良风团
（这里指美国天主教会在1934年成立的电影审查会）
[A级：可接受的；B级：不健康的；C级：遭天谴的]
不但将电影按照内容分级，
并且落实到具体行动，对不良的电影进行强烈抵制。
好莱坞承认了这一审查制度。
“海斯法典设置了一系列不可触犯的规矩。”
以下内容禁止在电影中出现：
激情的亲吻和拥抱，性倒错，性诱惑，强暴，堕胎，
卖淫和拉皮条，裸体，猥亵举动，亵渎。
这一禁令在Joe Breen
的负责管理下实行了约20年之久，
他的工作是修改台词，人物性格，和场景。
小说原作中对自己性取向感到困惑的而酗酒的主人公，
被改成了一个创作遇到瓶颈而酗酒的作家。
[1945年电影 《失去的周末》]
小说原作中一个反同性恋的凶杀犯
被改成了一个反犹太人的凶杀犯。
[1947年电影 《困境》]
Joseoh Breen[运动的官方发言人]：
“我们美国人民，是一群健康的，热爱家庭的人民。
那些对待生命的荒唐态度，
那些丑陋的反常性行为，
那些廉价的笑话，那些淫秽的言语，我们不需要。
体面的人们不会喜欢这些东西，
我们的任务就是要铲除它们，不让它们公之于众。”
-以前做过模特吗？
-不，没有。
我正在做一项关于
年轻女孩的头与肩膀的研究，
你不介意脱下外衣吧？
不，我不介意。
[1936年著名吸血鬼电影 《德古拉的女儿》]
你可以到那儿去脱衣服。
尽管作了很多工作，
这一运动并没有完全将同性恋从银幕中抹去，
只是让他们变得更难发现了。
他们现在有了新的形象
--例如冷血的恶棍。
我准备好了。
-是不是这些也要拿掉？
-是的。
你为什么这样看着我？
我有什么地方做错了吗？
事实上，你做得非常好。
你喜欢珠宝吗？
我有一些古老而又美丽的珠宝，
想看看吗？
我改变主意了，不想做了。
如果你不介意的话，我想要离开了。
别再靠近我了！
我不知道你在这儿，Danvers女士。
[1940年电影 《瑞贝卡》]
我只是担心窗户没有关紧，来查看一下。
你为什么会这么想，
我离开房间前可以将它们都关上的。
是你把窗户打开的吧？
“这部电影是一个典型的例子，
在其中似乎同性恋，或者说女同性恋
并没有出场。
但确实有一些东西，是明显地面向同性恋观众的，
那就是片名中提到的那个美丽女士，
瑞贝卡，她早就死去了，
从没有在这部电影的画面上出现过。
但她的前管家，Danvers女士，
却始终迷恋着她，尽管她早已死了。”
她的衣服我都完好地放置在这里。
看一看吧。
感觉一下吧。
这是Dewinter先生送的圣诞礼物。
整个一年，他不断地送她昂贵的礼物。
我把她的内衣收在这一边。
这是圣克莱尔修道院的修女为她特制的。
“她打开内衣柜的那幕，
是那么地有着美感。”
看，你可以透过它看到我的手。
“那些审查的人可不是火箭科学家，
他们放过了很多东西。
如果导演足够的狡猾，
他就能够在字里行间说话。”
安全起见，该花多少？
好吧，就这样办。
[1941年，电影《马其他之鹰》]
-栀子花香水。
-快让他进来。
“在这部电影中，我们还没见到Peter Lorre
就知道他是同性恋了，
我们知道外面的这个男人洒过了香水，
而且是栀子花的香水。
然后我们又听到俏皮的、东方的、
女性化的背景音乐。”
-请坐。
-多谢。
小说原著中并没有对Peter Lorre
这个角色有多少隐瞒。
小说中白纸黑字写着：这男人是个‘酷儿’。
（queer这个词在上世纪初贬义意味较多，
比Fag好不了多少。）
也许我可以为你搭挡的不幸惨死，
提供些安慰。
电影就只能暗示了，用一些露骨的言辞。
Spade先生，我仍然尝试着弄回那件装饰品，
也许，它没有放在该放的地方。
我希望你能帮助我。
那是一件小雕塑。黑色的，鸟。
而Alfred Hitchcock（希区柯克）则在一部电影中，
创造了不止一个，而是两个同性恋角色。
基于真实精神病病理学档案的一对同性恋人、
同时也是变态杀手 Leopold 和 Loeb。
[《绳索》 1948年电影]
Farley Granger(《绳索》的主演）：
“我们那时当然知道，这两个角色是同性恋，是的。
只是没有人去提起这事。
别忘了，那时可是1947年。”
“这是电影中重要的一幕。”
[左边的就是现在的叙述者Farley Granger]
-你有什么感觉吗？
-你指什么时候。
-...杀人时。
我说不清。
而且我好象不能完全记清发生的事。
我只记得，他瘫软下来，
然后我知道，结束了。
-然后呢？
-我感到一种让我自己都害怕的快感。
你又有什么感觉？
Arthur Laurents[《绳索》的编剧]:
“我想那时的审查员，并没有意识到
这是关于同性恋的镜头。
他们并没有意识到到底发生了什么，
所以这些镜头才能留下来。”
审查员有时侯会对一些女同性恋角色
睁一只眼闭一只眼，
只要她们安分一点，不要太露骨。
[《牢笼》 1950年电影]
-你好，Ann.
-你好，Harper.
自从你上楼为Benton工作以后，我总有点想念你。
这是Marie Allen,Benton女士安排她到洗衣房工作。
Maria马上就要生小孩了。
生孩子吗？你自己也还是个孩子啊。
-再见，Marie。
-再见，Anne。多谢你了
来把，先混得熟悉些吧。
别人也许会照顾你，但我可不会这样。
坐下吧，这样宽敞些。
“这一切都传达了某种社会信息：
‘进监狱很糟糕吗？’‘女人不温柔就很糟糕吗？’
‘女人硬派就很糟糕吗？’”
你叫什么名字，你是怎么弄伤手的？
我是个大女孩了，这又不是我第一天在外面混。
我的名字叫Marie Allen。
我已经拒绝了Kitty，
我想我也不会答应你的。
她是个可爱的鬼灵精。
[《双凰夺鸾》 1950年电影]
“在《双凰夺鸾》这部电影中，
出现了我最喜欢的代表“女同志”魅力的符号人物。”
她很有趣，不是吗？
那么单纯，一眼就能看穿。
早上起床后，知道该走出哪扇门，
这一定很好。
她就是这么平凡。
她也是个好歌手。
“我喜欢Lauren Bacall是因为当她早上醒来时，
她根本不知道接下来会发生什么。”
我等不及看看你其他的素描画了。
那我们先去吃晚餐，然后到我家去吧。
你光临宴会了，真不错啊，Richard。
这是我的丈夫。
这是Carson小姐，我和你提过她，她的画棒极了。
-很高兴认识你。
-那我九点再来找你。
-好的。
这真是个不错的宴会。
“许多女性就是看看电影，
然后回到上帝让她们待着的厨房，
而这些电影可以说对她们提出了警示。”
我们的婚姻到底算是什么啊？
你说你想多经历不同的事，
好吧，我成全你。
我准备离开你。
那我就杀了你。
你已经差点就杀死我了。
你有病，Amy,
你最好去看看医生。
“回顾50年代的情况，
那段时间就好象神话中平静海面的翠鸟。
人们仍然被这样教育：
不要发生种族战争，
不要碰毒品。
现在看起来那时好象是天堂。
但对于当时的我们，在亲身经历50年代时，
我们却觉得一切又无聊又愚蠢。
我想要以他为傲，
我一开始就是这样想，才生他的。
[1956年电影 《茶与同情》]
但他却让这一切变得如此困难。
我的同事问我，他想要做什么。
我只好说...他还没决定。
我就是说不出口，他想成为一个民谣歌手。
爱带来的悲伤折磨着我...
在50年代的美国，“男人气概”统治了一切。
“看上去象同性恋”和“是个同性恋”
得到的待遇是差不多的。
所以每个男人都要注意他自己的一举一动。
Tom，你走路的样子有点....
我只是想帮你！
上个礼拜前，
还他妈的没有人告诉我过该怎么走路！
好吧，我不管了。
-Al?
-怎么？
“《茶叶和同情》绝对是关于同性恋的电影。”
抱歉，告诉我走路有什么不对劲。
“这是一部关于怎么样‘矫正’同性恋的电影...
而需要被矫正的同性恋
在电影中只需要用一个词来代表：女人气。”
那，你走两步，让我来看看。
-我从来没有注意过你是怎么走的。
-好吧。
再走两步
-你不准和其他人说！
-我没那么傻。
[《无因的反叛》 1955年电影]
“我们知道Sal Mineo的角色是个同性恋
部分是因为他的衣柜上
贴了张艾伦.拉德[早期西部片影星]的照片。
部分是因为他对James Dean的角色表达的爱慕之情。”
你想到我家去坐坐吗？我家没有人。
Heck，我并不累，你累了吗？
我只是很难找到人聊聊天。
谁觉得容易呢？
Stewart Stern[《无因的反叛》的编剧]：
“人们一直在谈论，
影片中表达的到底是不是同性恋关系，
我本来的意图并没有着重于同性恋。
但是任何电影，不仅仅只是表达了作者的观点，
它也提供了观众一种机会，
去从中创造出他们所要的东西。”
你觉得冷吗？
“这电影是关于温情，
关于人与人之间可能的亲密关系，
它想要拓展爱的领域，
考虑到男人们的交往常常只是单向而乏味的。”
-我可以拿这衣服吗？
-否则你以为我在干什么？拿着。
“如果让我今天来写这个剧本的话，
我会对Plato这个角色描写的更加具体和细致。
我可能会这样写，
他被人群排斥所排斥，
因为每一个人都骂他是个‘死基佬’。
这一次，我会让他的孤立无援的感觉来源于此。”
-你们想干嘛？
-你知道我们想干嘛。
-我们要你的朋友！
-我们早就注意他了。
“对我来说，Sal Mineo
这一角色本身才是一种真正反叛。
他有值得反抗的东西，
那就是，在一个恐惧和厌恶同性恋的社会中，
去成为一个同性恋。
当然，他最后被杀害了。”
-把灯关了！
-Jim!
“这也是在我们的现实生活中真正发生的事。”
Gore Vidal
[已介绍过的获诺贝尔提名的老作家，
同时也是电影《宾虚》的编剧]
“你会变得擅长于将想说的东西放在潜台词中，
同时表面上一点没有提到它。
对我来说，写《宾虚》的剧本就是一个很好的例子。
[1959年电影 《宾虚》]
宾虚和米萨拉，
一个是犹太人，一个是罗马人
在少年时代结为好友。
而在电影的三个小时中，
他们面临的是政治敌对带来的互相仇恨，
但三个小时的电影都来讲仇恨并不行的通，
即使是象《宾虚》这种华丽的烂片。
电影的导演，William Wyler,问我，
‘你到底想做什么？’
我只是回答，‘让我尝试一些事。
让我们这样来看这两个青年人，
自从他们15、16岁分别后，他们再也没有见过对方。
他们曾经彼此相爱，
而现在他们重逢了，
这时罗马准备发动战争，
而由Stephen Boyd扮演的米萨拉，
则准备和由Charlton Heston扮演的宾虚
重叙旧情。
天知道他为什么这么做，但他确实这样做了。
毕竟，他是个罗马人。’
导演听完后，瞪者我，脸都白了，
我回答，‘放心，我不会直说的，不会公开宣扬什么
但我会很明确的表达出，
米萨拉爱上了宾虚。’
导演说，‘天呢，这可是宾虚啊，
我想副标题应该是象《基督教的传奇人物》这样吧。’
他含含糊糊地说。
导演最后说：‘好吧，这总比我们现在拍的这垃圾要好，
让我们试试。”
这么多年了啊，
- 我们还能这么亲密啊。
- 一拍即合。
“他说，‘你和别人说过了吗？’
我回答，‘没有。’
他说，‘你去告诉Boyd’，就是演米萨拉的演员，
‘但不要对Heston说（演宾虚的演员），
会出乱子的，让我来搞定。’
Heston一直以为他和Francis X. Bushman
演的是同一个角色，只是更安静些。
（Francis X. Bushman
在25年版本的《宾虚》出演宾虚，
基本是一个严肃的英雄人物。）
他的头一直保持这样，或者这样。
Stephin Boyd则完全明白，
将之在细节中完全表达出来了，
有几个眼神表达的再清楚不过了。
[右边的是Boyd]
-我说过，我会回来的。
-我没有想到你真的履行了。
我太高兴了。
-看看你。
-还是看看自己吧。
你都成保民官了。
我听到了这个消息时，为你干了一杯。
（保民官是罗马共和时代开始出现的官职，
对平民会议负责，对元老院或政府的法令有着否决权。
现代联合国的一票否决权‘Veto’来源于此。）
那我们再喝一杯吧。
[《红粉金枪》，1953年电影]
曾有一份秘密的爱情。
在我心中悄悄滋生。
好莱坞学会了在字里行间说话
而一小部分心领神会的观众
则学会了从字里行间解读。
天呀！
你是我见过的最美丽的东西。
我都不知道一个女人可以打扮成这样。
-你是怎么把那玩意儿撑起来的。
-真失礼！
“如果你是个同性恋观众，
你会习惯于把这些事情当作乐趣的：
你浏览整部电影，
只是为了找到某些穿着固定装束的角色。
这样你就可以暗自心想：这家伙绝对是个‘同志’。
[1954年电影 《荒漠怪客》]
“电影本身可能非常垃圾，
但你就是会乖乖地坐在荧幕前，
就是等着Joan Crawford
再一次地穿上黑色的牛仔装。”
我会杀了你的。
我知道你会。
前提是你没有被我先杀了。
“那时的同性恋观众们
极其渴望从电影中解读出什么。
我猜想所有的少数族群
都是带着某种盼望来看电影的。
他们会看到他们想看到的东西。
这就是为什么一千个人能看到一千个哈姆雷特。”
[《红河劫》 1948年电影]
让我们来帮个忙吧。
你用的这把枪可真是帅气啊，我能看看吗？
也许你也想看看我的。
棒极了，真是棒极了。
“Monty Clift和John Ireland这两个演员，
是知道他们暗示出了什么东西的，
正因为如此，这一幕演得那么有趣。
他们将手枪用作性暗示，
脸上还充满着喜悦。”
你知道吗，只有两样东西胜过一把好枪，
一块瑞士表，或者一个不知来历的女人。
你有瑞士表吗？
来吧，试试。
嘿，不错嘛。
你也不赖嘛。
再来。
“电影若要表达同性恋，大多会采取间接的方式，
最有趣的事情，
就是这恰好表达了现实中同性恋面临的情况，
我们只能间接表达我们自己，
就好象电影中的那些人只能间接表达他们自己。
就好象，角色被关在柜子里，
电影被关在柜子里，现实中的我们也被关在柜子里。”
[In the closet，在柜子里，
指同性恋隐藏自己的身份]
站在高高的山丘，
现在我放声高喊，
就算被说成是金黄的水仙，
总有一天，心门将会开放，
[1950年电影 《孤独地方》]
[1954年电影 《吉尔达》]
而我秘密的爱，再不需要隐藏。
一，二，三，四。
[1953年电影 《绅士爱美人》]
也有一些50年代的电影表达的同性恋
几乎都快摆上台面了。
Paul Rudnick：
[同性恋编剧，撰有《杰弗里》、《新郎向后跑》等剧本]
“你不可能把同性恋赶出电影，
就好象你不可能在现实中把同性恋给灭绝掉。
同性恋会从隐蔽的地方或者以隐蔽的方式登场，
在这部电影中，
明显整个健身房的男人们，
没有一个对女主演Jane Russel有兴趣，
他不用象海克力士，
（希腊神话中的大力神，宙斯与凡间女子私通所得。）
不用博学多闻，无所不知。
难道我在这儿就找不到爱吗？
甜蜜的爱。
真的吗？没有人吗？
来向我献殷勤啊，
大家都来吗？没有人吗？
没有人想玩玩？
“在50、60年代的很多和两性关系有关的喜剧中，
常常有一些可以被解读成同性恋的角色，
无论是托尼・兰德尔式的角色，
还是象‘装潢公司的老板’这样的角色。”
-就是这样了。
-恩，不错，地板是什么颜色？
[《娇凤痴鸾》 1961年电影]
淡紫色。
淡紫色？Leonard，谁会把厨房的地板弄成淡紫色？
我家厨房的地板就是。
哦，Leonard，
不是所有人都象你这样有艺术家气息的。
我们针对的客户是那些随处可见的普通人。
那些没品味的家伙...
“年复一年，在好莱坞，
形成了一种所谓的‘DF’电影
所有的桃乐丝黛（著名演员，歌手，外形甜美）
的电影都可以看作‘DF’电影
‘DF’代表‘被延迟的性’
意思是男女主人公在结婚前不会作爱。
在结婚前没有性爱。
这曾经在好莱坞是雷打不动的金律。”
多么棒的一个男人啊，我真希望他是单身汉。
我不知道这要付出多少，但我相信她值得我冒个险。
[《枕边细语》 1959年电影]
“Rock（指著名同性恋演员Rock Hudson）
家里有个放映室，
他喜欢把他的客人带去，播放老电影给他们看。
我认识的许多人，都很喜欢看桃乐丝黛的老电影。”
“我想我们看这些电影感到有趣的原因之一，
是因为几乎所有的轻喜剧中，
都有很多同性恋才懂的笑话，
比如Rock Hudson扮演的角色，
总会多多少少摆出一副同性恋的模样，
为了让女人放松警惕，好能将她搞上床，
谈谈你的工作吧。
和颜色、布料什么的打交道，一定很令人激动吧，
十分反讽的是，
一个同性恋演员，扮演一个异性恋角色，
而这个角色，又要在戏中假装成一个同性恋。
多好吃啊，
如果我能知道这东西的配方该多好。
回家看妈咪的时候，一定能让她高兴的。
[《热情似火》 1959年电影]
“我们本来就是半男半女的，
我们从精子和卵子中来的，不是吗？
所以当我在演《热情如火》的时候，
我心里就想着格蕾丝・凯丽
（老牌女影星，主演《乡村姑娘》等）
我想着我的母亲，
还稍微带一点伊夫・阿登的感觉
(老牌女星，常出演热情的角色）。”
-我的名字是Josephine.
-我是Daphne.
“我的上唇有点太细小了，
所以每次我不讲话，我就摆出这样的姿势。”
-天。
-你不用担心这个，
我们才不想被别人发现是男人呢。
那种八个手的多毛的禽兽。
“我们的性征常常互相交叠，
有的时候我们强硬，有的时候我们温和。
这种交叠就在这部电影里面，微妙地表达出来。”
Osgood，我不能和你住一起，
我们不可能结婚的！
为什么？
首先，我的金发是假的。
我不介意。
我喜欢抽烟，我抽得很凶。
我无所谓的。
我声名狼籍，过去三年我都和一个萨克斯手同居。
我可以原谅你。
我生不了孩子。
我们可以领养啊。
你不明白，Osgood。
我是男人。
不要紧，没有人是十全十美的。
当同性恋主题渐渐变得严肃起来，
当性的问题开始被涉及，
结果就是对场景开始编辑，剪裁。
[《斯巴达克斯》1960年电影]
Antoninus，西西里人，27岁。
歌手。
你平时怎么应用这一天赋的，恩？
我教我主人的儿子，
我同时也教他们阅读经典著作。
经典吗？
我正在考虑，既然你这么有天赋，该怎么安排你呢？
你应该做我的贴身仆人。
你跟着他们学。
其他人，过来。
“你第一次看到Antoniniu,他站在一群人中间，
然后那个男人说，‘我要他作我的贴身仆人。’
这个词听上去很简单，贴身仆人，
它到底是什么意思？
他说了贴身仆人这个词，然后下一个场景
我们在浴盘中，我扮演的Antoniniu为他擦洗身子。”
[被删除的场景]
来这儿。
“我们之间简单地聊天，
然后他和我说，
‘Antoniniu，你喜欢吃蜗牛吗？’
我说‘恩，还算喜欢。’
‘那么牡蛎呢？’
‘这个恐怕不喜欢。’”
你觉得吃蜗牛是道德的，
而吃牡蛎就是不道德的吗？
不，主人。
当然。
这只关乎品味，不是吗？
是的，主人。
品味和胃口可是不一样的，
因此，它和道德无关，不是吗？
“你甚至从那个远镜头中都可以看出，
我扮演的角色开始明白他在说什么，
我回答‘是的，主人。’
然后他说‘我既喜欢蜗牛，也喜欢牡蛎。’
我的角色意识到，
他将要做一些他并没有预料到要做的事。
我喜欢Antoniniu的性格，你知道吗？
带我去吃一顿丰盛的晚餐，
而不要只就这样把我扔到浴盆里，把肥皂丢给我。”
我的品味既包括蜗牛，也包括牡蛎。
“他们把这一幕删剪了。”
“在这以前，我从来没有见识过审查制度。”
因为你的朋友Skipper的死，你才开始拼命喝酒的，
这是事实。
[1958年电影 《朱门巧妇》]
“他们把《朱门巧妇》这电影一剪再剪。
他们不能允许Brick（片中的主人公）
对他的好兄弟有任何性方面的欲求。”
你是什么意思。
-没什么，只是...
-只是什么，老实说！
快说！
-你为什么这么激动。
-管那么多！快说！
-你为什么要大喊大叫？
-Skipper和我只是朋友而已。
-你明白吗？
-他们都说Skipper是...
Skipper是这个世界上我唯一信任的人。
-我不允许你玷污这份感情。
-冷静点。
你偏要把它说成可耻和丑陋的，你...
“对能看懂的观众来说，一切都是很清楚的。
但你就是不能把这些词给说出来。
在电影《突如其来的夏天》中我遇到过这种情况，
田纳西・威廉斯写的剧本。”
（美国现代最负盛名的剧作家，
名剧有《欲望号街车》等，同性恋者。）
你知道我为什么这样做。
我告诉过你，我是他的人。
[《突如其来的夏天》1959年电影]
Sebastian很孤单，医生。
“道德审查会由这个狡猾的耶稣会教士领导。
[耶稣会是天主教为对抗新教于16世纪成立的精英集团]
我至少和他有过五次会面。
‘你不能这么说’‘你不能那么说’
而删剪完了后，电影也就没剩下什么了。”
Sebastian只不过是在利用你罢了。
-利用？
-我的意思是年轻，吸引人。
她要么在说胡话，要么在说谎。
他离开她的家，因为她不再吸引他了。
-因为你偷了他的心。
-因为她不再吸引他。
一个母亲和一个儿子间能有什么吸引？
-我告诉你...
-这些谎话该停止了。
除非你把我的头给割了。
“这就好象在苏维埃政权下的克里姆林宫中工作，
就象为他们的《真理报》写文章。
[苏维埃政权下办立的以宣传纲领为主要目的报纸]
你必须要学会怎么在字里行间说话，
怎么在画面和画面之间提供暗示。
你可以利用某种表情，
或通过对赫本的脸的特写来达到目的。
比如当伊丽莎白.泰勒正带领赫本，
一步步靠近真相。
道德审查会又不让我们直接说出这一真相。”
-我们只不过是诱饵。
-诱饵？
Sebastian的诱饵，他在利用我们。
当她不再能够为他将更多的鱼引诱到网中，
他就不要她了。
诱饵？用作什么？鱼是指什么？
我们在为他拉皮条。
“Sebastian喜欢男人吗？
事实上，在影片的结尾，他被活活给生吞了，被一群...
不得不承认的是，这是田纳西写的所有作品中，
最有戏剧感的一幕。”
他想要逃跑，
他逃向大楼旁的人行道，
那些人从四面八方涌来，
只能向山顶跑了，
Sebastian Venable代表了在那个时代
同性恋在电影中的典型形象。
一个没有脸，也没有台词的人。
他的存在如同是一个怪物，
因此他会象怪物那样死去。
这些场景甚至都是对早期恐怖片的某种刻意模仿。
[《科学怪人的新娘》 1935年]
（顺便说一句，科学怪人弗兰克林系列的导演是同性恋，
推荐电影《众神与野兽（Gods&Monsters）》，
以他的生平为蓝本。）
我不知道他怎么能跑这么远，
他平时不怎么跑步的。
但他就这样跑啊，跑啊，跑啊！
他没有跑到终点。
没有。
他们赶上了他。
他只叫喊了一声。
然后我，我...
救命啊！
“这部电影公演后，纽约时报抨击了，
‘这部由一群堕落者弄出的堕落的电影’。
你会看到Bosley Crowther
（《纽约时报》著名电影评论家）的一篇文章这样说
‘如果你喜欢乱伦、强奸、鸡奸、食人、堕落...
这部电影最适合你了，这部变态的电影。’
结果每个美国人都去看了，
这篇评论造就了这部电影。”
[这部电影只供成年人观赏]
一部最为惊险最为猎奇的电影，
[字幕：揭示真实，力量惊人的电影《受害者》]
当好莱坞还在遮遮掩掩时，
英国的电影抢先迈出了一步，
[墙上写着：Farr是个死同性恋。]
由Dirk Bogarde
出演了荧幕上的第一个同性恋英雄。
我想要知道真相。
我想知道为什么他上吊自杀。
[1961年电影 《受害者》]
他被人勒索。
-这是他偷窃的原因吗？
-是的。
有人发现他是个同性恋，然后勒索他？
是的。
找到敲诈他的把柄，说明他一定有伴侣了。
他的伴侣是你吗？是你吗？
“这部电影有一个场景，主人公直率地表达出了
想要和另一个男人作爱的欲望。
要知道，在1961年，对一个主流界的知名演员来说，
这要冒多大风险啊。”
好吧，我告诉你。
你不刨根问底是不满意的是吧。
你一定要逼我说是吧。
我不再去见他，正是因为我想要占有他。
你明白吧，我想要占有他！
回到好莱坞，60年代审查制度逐渐开始松动。
在限制中成长起来的一代电影人，
开始打碎这最后的禁忌。
[画面显示：除了“性倒错”，其他的限制都被取消了]
同性恋终于可以在电影中被讨论。
但是仍然是一件不会在正派人们的口中谈论的事情。
[《双姝怨 》 1962年电影]
我们还看到了一些事。
-什么事。
-坏事，我不能告诉你。
你这样让我更烦躁了，想说，就说吧。
我的意思是，我不能大声说，我要悄悄告诉你。
-为什么你要悄悄说呢？
-我不知道，我就是觉得应该这样。
“当我们制作这部电影的时候，
关于同性恋还没有任何真正公开的讨论。”
你知道你刚才说了什么吗？
“这只是一个孩子的指控罢了，什么事都有可能。”
把车停下，John！把车停下！
Shirley Maclaine[女演员，《双妹怨》主演之一]
那时我们没有人知道，
我们可能会成为先驱，
而且我们也表达的也不尽完美，
我们还处在一种思维定势中，
我们其实并不理解我们表达的人和事。”
我一定要告诉你，你一定要听，
我不能再隐瞒下去了。
我是罪人！
你什么罪也没有犯！
放到今天，这部电影会被喝倒彩，
也许它确实应该被喝倒彩。
今天的观众不能接受女主角Martha说
“哦，我是个罪人，我太肮脏了，我把你毁了。”
观众会认为，她应该和这一切作斗争。
她就是喜爱女孩子，她应该为之作斗争。
因此当今天的观众看到Martha的这些表现，
他们根本不会思考这些话说明了什么，
这些对话后面可能隐藏着什么样的抉择。
这变化让人惊奇。我不知道这是为什么。”
难道你看不出来吗？
我不能再忍受你这样抚摩我。
我不能再忍受你这样看着我。
这一切都是我的错。
我毁了你的生活，我也毁了我自己的。
我不想这样的。
我不是故意要这样的。
哦，我是多么的病态和肮脏啊，我不能再忍受了！
“这个话题本身所揭示出的东西，
我们当时排演的时候根本没有意识到。
我和Audrey从来没有谈论过此事。
这难道不有趣吗？
真的很有趣。”
“她憎恨着自己，她觉得自己是变态的，
这些情景我现在看到了还想流泪。
然后我会开始想：
为什么我想哭呢？为什么这种感觉现在还有呢？
这只是部愚蠢的老电影。
现在的我们已经不会这么看待自己了。
但事实上，这种说法并不正确。
我们现在仍然会有片中主人公的这种感觉。
我们现在似乎已经完全接受这些标签：
“我们是快乐的，我们为自己骄傲，我们适应的很好，
我们是酷儿(queer)，是另类的，
人本来就是双性恋的。”
但无论我摆出多少先锋的姿势，
比如‘我在卫道士看来就是堕落的，我为之高兴。’
仍然有一部分的我这样想，
为什么偏偏是我？为什么我会是个同性恋？”
他让我转告你，在你继续做这事之前，
可别忘了在夏威夷发生的那事，
然后他就挂电话了。
在夏威夷发生了什么事情，Brig？
[1962年电影  《华府千秋》]
那个声音听起来怎样？
令人毛骨悚然。
听上去就好象他知道什么肮脏的秘密一样。
我前两天上了头版，
难免会接到这种电话的。
下次再接到，你就直接挂了。
“我第一次看这部电影的时候，在上高中，
那时候我还是个处子，
25岁前我都没有和任何人作过爱。
所以对我来说，这些事还没有亲身体验。
就在那时，我从电影中看到了正等待着我的那条路。
让我倾听这嗓音，
这充满秘密的嗓音，
它想诉说些什么，
“片中的男主人公，Senator Brigham Anderson，
受到了勒索信。
他前往与他的旧情人会面，在这个酒吧。
我在这部电影中第一次窥探到我一直想知道的东西，
一种稳定有组织的同性恋生活，
-----然而它是非常，非常地提心吊胆的。
因为我们只能生活在影子里，把自己隐藏起来。”
嘿，过来啊，别只是傻站着。
别跑啊。
Ray,别忘了你现在可是和我在一起的。
Brig?
-等一等，Brig，听我解释。
-出租车！
-听我解释，Brig。
我需要钱，Brig!
你不会再见到我的。我打电话给你，只是因为喝醉了。
快开车！
“我立刻意识到这些可怕的事情也会发生在我身上，
而我将无法回头，一旦我和另一个男人作爱。
这条路的尽头将会是自杀。
这些印象都是从电影中获得的。”
是Brig吗？
怎么了？
他死了
Brig死了？
他割断了自己的喉咙，在他的办公室。
Oliver看到你了，一个下午和Dove混在一起。
你对我说谎，Haley
[《沿着荒凉之地行走》 1962年电影]
哦，好吧，也许等你成熟点，会变好的。
你想要我怎么个成熟法？
变得和你一样？
我想知道你和那个男孩之间到底发生了什么？
你和那个德克萨斯的臭乡巴佬恋爱了吗？
我们的关系还要更进一步。
已经无法挽回了是不是？你想让他快乐是不是？
-你想让他美梦成真，甚至和他结婚。
-也许我们会结婚的。
好吧，我很遗憾我将失去你。
如果你觉得这个世界都是你的囊中之物的话，
你就顺着自己心意做吧。
你有没有想过，如果那个男孩发现了真正的你，
发现了你所作过事，你该怎么办？
-他会原谅我的。
-那好吧，去吧。
毕竟，象你这样的女孩有足够资本吸引男人，
有足够能力去伤他的心。
-我会改变的。
-说说容易。
你以前不也说过很多次吗？
为什么不现在就跑去告诉他呢？
告诉他Harley Gerard的日日夜夜是怎样渡过的。
告诉他这些年来你在个怎样的烂泥堆里打滚。
去啊，告诉他啊。
Barry Sandler[同性恋剧作家]
“对于我们这些成长在60年代的人来说，
同性恋形象永远都是悲惨的，
我们从电影中得到这样的印象：
同性恋永远是绝望的，倾向于自我毁灭和自杀。”
我也有可能偶然地变成....变成和他们一样的人
[《侦探》 1968年电影]
这种想法让我害怕，也让我愤怒和恶心。
于是我去了一次码头，我对那里早就耳闻。
人们谈起那里的时候，
总是咯咯地笑着，极尽挪揄之能。
我以前也有过两次这样的经验....
一次在大学，一次在军队。
我本以为我已经把这种念头完全躯散了...
可是我并没有。
我看着他们。
我也可能成为他们中的一员吗？
哦，天哪。
扭曲的脸庞，无家可归的可怜处境。
无法在阳光下公开地生活，
总是被各种危险的阴影所笼罩。
人们总是意识不到我们要经历多少痛苦。
比如抚养我成长的家庭，
他们甚至根本就不承认世界上有“同性恋”这回事。
这就是我的处境，我对之无能为力。
我没有退路。
“这些电影场景，夸大了我们的悲惨，
夸大了我们对世界的憎恨。
似乎在预言：这世界上永远也不会有人爱我们。”
你怎么会到现在还没结婚呢？
[1968年电影 《狐狸》]
你长得并不难看。
又是个好人。
有双漂亮的腿，
和漂亮的脚踝。
为什么没有个好男人陪伴你呢？
我想问题在你自己身上。
“我觉得美国文学、戏剧、电影中
创造了这种‘同性恋的宿命’，
而且这种宿命，
还被其他那些挑战传统两性关系的人物共同分享着。”
Haley？
带Jo离开这里！
“你必须赎罪。你必须受难。
如果你是个通奸的女人，你只会被人指指点点，
而如果你是个喜欢女人的女人，你最好快快上吊。
这更象是将罪恶分出层次。如果你是个同性恋，
只有一种忏悔方式：去死。”
你走进酒吧的那刻，我就知道你也是同性恋。
你怎么知道的？
我们就是能互相辨认。
[电影《侦探》]
也许是从走路的样子，
也许是从眼神的交流，
你怎么了？
别来折磨我！
我要叫警察了！
-别！
-接线生。
你这个婊子！
现在有一点很清楚，
这部片子的主人公的形象已经成为了一种固定模式：
一个无法确定自己性取向的家伙，
一步步毁灭自身，毁灭旁人。
老老实实呆着，把你的诡计留着自己用，否则....
杀了她！杀了她！
哦，Martha...
等轮到你自己的时候，
看你还有没有胆子。
你以为戏里面演的都是真的吗？
不是所有“同志”都会在故事的结尾砰地崩了自己的。
-一，二。一，二。
-哦，天。
-单脚，单脚，蹲下。一 ，二，三。
-等一下。
[《乐队男孩》1970年电影]
象群老年的踢踏舞演员。
改变终于发生了：
在这部好莱坞电影中，
同性恋第一次开始艰难的审视自己的生活,
这感觉就象引起轰动的月经！
作为对以往同性恋形象的扭转，
这电影中的人们都好好地活着。
“这部电影带给我非常大的影响。
那时我还没有公开自己的‘同志’身份。
这部电影带给我这样的印象：
同性恋之间存在的那份认同感和友情真是棒极了，
这种强烈的‘我是这个团体的一份子’的感受，
我从未在其他任何地方得到过。”
忘了你的烦恼。
来吧，快乐起来。
什么也不要去想。
是不是觉得没有比看同性恋模仿茱蒂佳兰
(著名女星，《绿野仙踪》中桃乐丝的扮演者）
更无聊的事了？
有的，那就是看同性恋模仿蓓蒂.戴维丝。
（另一著名百老汇女星）
Mart Crowley[《乐队男孩》的编剧]
“我碰到的很多人都喜欢这些人物。
我想说，片中的这九个男孩，
都可以说是某一部分的我。
Michael,我就是这样一个人，
32岁，长得抱歉，麻脸，
犹太人，花枝招展的“同志”。
如果说面对这样的自己，
要花些时间才能振作，
如果说要以这样的面貌来面对世界，
需要一些勇气，一些烟草
那也是我自己的事情，我会好好面对的。
我倒要问问你，今晚过得怎么样？
“他们确实不幸又暴躁，
如果我将他们描写得有什么缺陷的话，
那一定反映了，呃，我自己身上存在着同样这些缺陷。
但这确实是我看问题的方式。”
你是个又伤心又可悲的家伙，
你是个同性恋，
你不愿意承认这一点。
但这是你无法改变的事。
你再怎么祈祷上帝也没用。
你再怎么相信精神分析，想借助这来安稳渡过余生
也没有用。
你可能有一天非常熟练地过着你的异性恋生活，
如果你那么渴望成为个异性恋的话。
如果你真的想抑制你的激情，去这样生活的话。
但哪怕这样，你骨子里还是一个同性恋。
骨子里，micheal。
骨子里。
一直到你死去的那天。
朋友....
这真是个开心的宴会啊。
“我觉得这种自我否定，自我抨击的幽默感，
源自于一种，呃，
对自己的鄙视，如果你愿意这么说。
这大概来源于整个时代对同性恋的看法。
那时，同性恋仍然被当作一种精神疾病，
如果你进入一家同性恋酒吧，
你会被合法地逮捕，
对同性恋酒吧的随意搜查也是合法的。
我对这一切再熟悉不过了。
那时人们不只是在态度上敌视同性恋，
人们把这写进了法律。
法律否定我们这些人的存在...
而且是从根本上否定。”
要是我们能不那么憎恨自己，该有多好。
该有多好，你知道。
要是我们能学会不那么憎恨自己，
哪怕只是少憎恨一点。
[旗子上写着“同性恋解放阵线”]
注：1969年6月27日，警察对纽约格林威治村
克里斯托佛大街的石墙酒吧，进行了突然袭击，
引起了同性恋抗议，约有400多名同性恋
高呼“同性恋权力”与警察发生暴力冲突。
这标志着“同性恋解放运动”时代的开始。
于是1969年7月底，纽约成立首次用“同性恋”命名
并与“解放”口号联系起来的组织“同性恋解放阵线”,
石墙骚乱的斗争口号和同性恋解放阵线,
迅速在全国的左派与激进派中扩散开来，
一年间扩散到了全国的校园和城市，
同性恋解放运动正式诞生.
“据我所知，第一部不以同性恋身份为耻的电影，
是《卡伯雷歌厅》，
[1972年电影 《卡伯雷歌厅》]
它描写的东西，
很接近于当时旧金山的同性恋的生活状态：
成为一个同性恋并没有那么大的负担。”
我的身体是不是让你充满欲望？
没有吗？
你的身体很好看。
你真的这么觉得吗？
我很注意我自己的身材的，
你看，这里很平。
屁股也很好，
还有...这儿。
太白天的，还是不要这样吧。
大概是因为你从不和女孩睡觉。
哦。
你确实...
听着，我们基本上算是共用一套公寓，
如果你只喜欢男孩，我不会来纠缠你的。
告诉我，你和不和女孩睡觉？
一般人不会就这样问别人这种事的。
但我会问的。
Jay Presson Allen（《歌厅》的编剧）
“这个男孩是个同性恋，
而他看上去很理智，很绅士。
这个故事就是这样的。
没有任何焦躁不安的角色。”
哦，你干脆去和maximillian胡搞吧。
我确实这样做了。
我也和他做过了...
“然后，事情开始改变，比你想象的快很多...”
-你又是谁？
-我是Bernstein。
-你是犹太人？
-不，亲爱的，我是同性恋。
[《下一站格林威治村》 1976年电影]
我不知道你怎么看，我觉得你是个很棒的舞者，
你也不赖啊。
Antonio Fargas
[《下一站格林威治村》《洗车》主演]：
“我觉得描写一个黑人同性恋，
相对于描写一个白人同性恋，
比较不会引起一般人的反感，
为什么？这很难说。
但我可以提供一种解释，
就好象用情景喜剧的方式来表现我们的生活，
相对用严肃的正剧来表现，
比较不会引起一般人的反感。这道理是相通的。
但是，喜剧确实可以揭示很多东西。”
[1976年电影 《洗车》]
快滚开，你这个长得抱歉的‘死基佬’。
你说谁长得抱歉呢？
笑什么，她根本不好笑。
她只是另一个例子，
我们的男人是怎么被这个时代摧毁的。
亲爱的，我比你更象个男人，
也比你所能得到的人更象个女人。
操！
但是，同性恋在电影中的露脸，
也伴随着一个不利之处，
对同性恋报复性的恐吓开始无处不在。
[1971年电影 《洗车》]
Tom Hanks：
“我是在这部电影中第一次看到同性恋形象的，
搭便车的人，出现在《粉身碎骨》中。”
对不起，能告诉我们你要开往何处吗？
我要去Frisco（旧金山的简称），
哦，太好了，多谢。
“其中的一个家伙拿着个女式提包，
他们穿着非常紧身的衣服。
他的脸上有着某种挑逗性的表情。”
你为什么笑？
我没笑。
你笑了。
是因为你觉得我们是同性恋，不是吗？
这个东西能说明我们是强盗。
强盗？
你为什么笑，Mary？
“大家都会叫好，当看到这汽车以时速60英里
穿过一个车站，然后这两个男人被扔下车。
我们都觉得这棒极了，我们会大叫
‘你还记得那幕吗，那两个同性恋被扔下车？’
我们觉得它拍得很精彩，
这就是同性恋在我们心中留下的形象。
同性恋就意味着穿紧身衣，挑逗的淫荡的视线，
还得拿个女式提包。”
Ron Nyswaner(《费城故事》编剧）
我有一次进一家剧院。
投入地欣赏一部精彩的电影。
突然间，冒出一个被认为是同性恋的角色，
是故事中的坏蛋，杀手，
最后被杀了。
这时观众席中爆发出雷鸣般的掌声。
我和朋友一起看的这部电影。
[电影《弗雷比和比恩 》，]
这是一个易装癖杀手，打斗时还做着芭蕾动作，
当然，我们的英雄耀武扬威地掏出了枪，
向这个易装癖拼命地开枪，
观众爆发出了雷鸣的掌声。
我想人们是这样想的：
人们确实在为坏蛋的死鼓掌，
但他们也在为同性恋的死鼓掌。”
“你知道你在看一部‘异性恋电影’，
你知道这就是规矩，
但是你仍然....仍然没有充分地准备好这样被人侮辱。”
[《夜班》 1982年电影]
你知道，到了这个份上，
我什么堕落的事都做的出来。
看来我错了。
[1985年电影 《青年狼人》]
你是不是准备告诉我你是个‘死基佬’？
我可承受不起这个消息。
我才不是个死基佬。
我是个狼人。
“我从来不会在电影中听到
‘黑鬼’（对黑人的污蔑性称呼）这个词，
除非是一对黑人在打情骂俏。
或者是一个古板的南方警长。
这符合一种固定形象。
为了表达他的古板性格，
他得用这个词。
但‘死基佬’这个词可不一样。
这个词...任何人都可以对任何人用。”
嘿，这个餐厅不是有‘死基佬’不准入内的规矩吗？
嘿，怎么跪下了？
你是个没骨气的同性恋？
我知道你想干嘛，你这个死基佬。
该让大家都知道你这死基佬般的样子。
我看你不应该再和那个死基佬混在一起了。
觉得不爽，死基佬？
你个死基佬，你个肮脏的同志。
-你是同志吗？
-不，长官。
怎么了，你也变得和死基佬一样了？
怎么，你要对我做死基佬做的事？
哦，你个死基佬还和我玩硬的？
你们这群死基佬想干嘛？
听到了吗，你个死基佬？
-操，死基佬。
-操，死同志。
-这个死基佬是谁？
-你个秃头的死基佬警察。
“你只有两种选择，习惯它，或者强迫地接受它，
这种称呼压倒性的流行起来。
它成为了人们看待同性恋的方式。”
当好莱坞开始熟悉这些急速增多的同性恋场景，
它又开始将场景放置到皮革酒吧，
以创造某种毛骨悚然的气氛，
[《虎口巡航》1980年电影]
-有多大？
-够出来混了。
-上还是下？
-都可以。
-我不帮别人服务的。
-没关系。
口交？肛交？
“我有过一次《虎口巡航》的经历，
不是指看这部电影，
而是成为看过这部电影的人欺辱的对象。
我和我的爱人，被一群在电影院工作的人殴打，
他们威胁我们，追逐我们出电影院，一直到街上，
当我逃脱其中一个人的追逐时，
他向我喊着，
‘如果你看过《虎口巡航》，你知道你会有什么下场。’”
看看是谁？
是我。
还有你。
我开始害怕了。
同性恋的角色发生了变化，
从受害者，到凶手。
[1980年电影 《窗》]
脱了。
把毛衣脱了。
[1981年电影 《夺命影迷》]
[《虎口巡航》]
求求你，求求你。
是你求我的。
[同性恋组织在抗议《虎口巡航》]
停止《虎口巡航》的播映！
同性恋回击了！
[屏幕显示：20世纪福克公司骄傲地推出
我们最诚实和最有争议性的电影]
有一部电影大胆地喊出了，
同性恋是爱的行为，而不是暴力行为。
[电影名：《作爱》]
所以，好莱坞必须对公众相应地作出些警示。
[屏幕显示：
《作爱》成功地描绘了一位年轻的女性行政管理
员的肖像，关于她怎样尝试理解她的丈夫――他
正面临一次人生的转折：该怎样面对自己的性取向。
《作爱》直率而公开地讲述了一个细致优雅
的故事。它并不是完全讲述性。但对于某些观众，
仍然可能过于激烈。
《作爱》有裸镜，但非常温和。我们为它的
诚实而骄傲，我们为它的勇气而鼓掌。
Barry Sandler[《作爱》的编剧]：
“那时是1982年，电影中还未有过任何同性恋主角，
这是一个飞跃。”
事实是，我写的很多东西是真实发生的。
[1982年电影 《作爱》]
我是个作家，
我必须对新事物敏锐些。
尝试不同的事情。
你为什么不干脆点说出来呢。
我是同性恋。
说的好。
不客气。
Daniel Melnick[《作爱》的制作人]：
“选角是非常难的，
这两个男主角非常难找，
选定的主演Harry Hamlin和
Michael Ontkean一直犹豫着，
他们身边的所有人告诉他们，
不要去演同性恋，
说这会毁了他们的事业。”
Harry Hamlin[《作爱》主演之一]
“至少在80年代早期，这些忌讳还是存在的。
我不知道现在怎么了，
但那个时候，好莱坞更象是个牛仔们的圈子，
一个异性恋的牛仔圈子。
我们的内心深处多多少少有些恐同情绪，
我自己如果看到一个演员饰演一个同性恋角色，
仍然会心想：‘哇，这家伙自己就是个同志吧。’
为什么会这样想，我也不知道。
然后我才会告诉自己：‘别傻了，
你自己也演过，你知道是怎么回事。’
但是，为什么我们这么在意这个问题？
而又是谁会特别在意这些问题？”
我来吧。
“那时工作室正好在换手中，
一个新的老板过来，他不是电影界的，
不是知识分子，
也不是文艺界的，
在放映室为他，他的妻子和女儿，
试映这部电影，是一个艰难的任务。
电影还未剪辑完成，
我的同事都没有去，他们都有些害怕，
我一个人去了，坐在最后，
他则坐在那小小放映室的前方。
放映时，他显然有点坐不住，不断抖动，
放到两个男人拥抱和亲吻的时候，
他跳起来喊：‘你他妈地拍了部死基佬的电影！’，
然后走了出去。”
“首演的那天，我正好在迈阿密，
我们坐下，电影开始放映，
随着电影情节发展，
你可以感到观众变得越来越不自在，
对银幕上的场景不自在。
这种不自在逐步增强
当他们开始亲吻，你可以感到观众炸开了。
人们恐慌起来，一片喧哗，
人们纷纷离席，于是我也赶快离开了。”
“主流的观众不喜欢同性恋场景，
主要是他们想到同性恋之间的性爱，
就觉得不舒服。
看到同性恋这样做，
意味着他们自己也可以做这样的事，
这让他们很不舒服。
这就好象那个有名的笑话：
‘我讨厌吃豌豆，我很高兴我讨厌它们。
因为如果我不讨厌，我就会去吃它们，
然后我会讨厌它们。’”
[1927年电影 《铁翼雄风》]
[屏幕显示：
你知道，世界上没有比你的友谊更宝贵的事情了。]
曾经有一段时间，男人能很自然地
在屏幕上表达他们之间的温情。
[屏幕显示：
我知道，一直知道]
但随着人们对同性恋知道的越多，
男人与男人之间的情感越来越被认为是罪恶的。
[1968年电影 《军官》]
亲吻会被当作是冒犯。
或者某种恶意中伤。
[1962年电影 《桥上的风景》]
让我来告诉你，你算个什么东西。
你是个什么东西。
[1974年电影 《霹雳炮与飞毛腿》]
你竟敢...我要杀了你！
John Schlesinger:[《血腥星期天》的导演]
“美国人可能特别害怕有关性的问题，
他们可以展示各种形式的暴力，
但牵涉到性的问题，
我想美国人变得...以自己为绝对正确，
还会作出些愚蠢的行为：
假装和自己不同的东西是不存在的。”
[1971年电影 《血腥星期天》]
你还好吧？
“当时对这个吻争议很大。
编剧认为这一幕应该在黑暗中，仅仅显出轮廓，
我说：‘不行，它应该自然地发生。’
就好象在现实中那样。”
人们似乎对两个男人亲热的看法，
和对两个女人亲热的看法，非常不同。
[1982年电影 《活着就是为了作证》]
“人们很喜欢看女性的裸体，少女气质，
女孩子间的亲密关系。
人们觉得这很性感，很有情欲
女人们不会觉得这场面对她们有什么威胁。
男人们要么根本不觉得受到威胁，
要么对这种场面心痒不已。”
“异性恋男人比较不能容忍
两个男人作爱的场景。
因为他们觉得这意味着你很懦弱，
人们总是把‘懦弱’和‘好男色’联系起来，
却根本没有意识到这是种荒唐的理论。
这就是为什么男人总喜欢粗声粗气地说
‘我是个大男人。’
好象成为一个男人
取决于你身边的人是谁似的。”
[1985年电影 《紫色》]
在《紫色》这部电影中，
Celie爱上了Shug.
她们是两个互相相爱的女人，
这种亲密并不是和性有关。
我觉得其中有着更深厚的感情。
-我们走吧。
-你是什么意思？
人们就是更能接受两个女子的亲密行为，
而不是两个男子。
这就象个巨大的禁忌一样。
[1991年电影 《末路狂花》]
你肯定吗？
是的。
来吧。
Susan Sarandon[《末路狂花》主演]：
“当我在《末路狂花》的结尾进行这一吻，
来让人们屏息时，
我和Geena说了些话，没对别人说过，
我说我觉得她们之间的情感是爱，而不是身体的吸引。
就好象攀登悬崖，
换作你绝对不能象她们这样坚持下去。
对我来说，她们的所作所为如同一次宣告，
关于....
你看，她们能说出对方要说的话，
她们一直支持着对方，
就好象经典西部片《神枪手与智多星》中的一样。
除了她们没有中弹倒下。”
[1969年电影 《神枪手与智多星》]
“想想如果神枪手与智多星这两个家伙――
当然，这样他们就有更多理由被追杀了，
如果这两个家伙最后亲吻了会怎么样。
但他们的做派就和老电影里其他男人的做派一样
他们把他们的枪拿出来，
因为他们不能把他们的‘老二’掏出来。
他们把枪掏出来，这样结伴着，然后落幕，
男人就是喜欢这样做。”
你在挑逗我吗，Blaylock小姐？
[《饥渴》 1983年电影]
Miriam。
我并不是不知道。Sarah.
“一开始的剧本就好象《花花公子》上登的小文章
有很多做作的姿势，还有贴身内衣，
没有真正动人的戏剧场景。
我觉得真正算得上性感的，
是两人第一次互相触碰的时候。
我特别强调那一幕，
她把酒洒在她身上，
她递给她东西，
她们触碰，亲吻，
然后你就看到窗帘遮住了她们的身体。
值得一提的是，他们都觉得
我扮演的角色应该是喝醉了，
他们觉得这是她作出这种事情的唯一解释。
我坚持不是这样。
你并不是一定要喝醉才能和凯瑟琳・德纳芙
（著名法国女星，片中另一位主演）上床。
我甚至觉得这和以前的性经历没关系。
我只是觉得，这个角色如果是清醒着做这些事，
会更有趣。
无论是好是坏，似乎女人并不真的觉得
女性之间发生亲密行为会是件严重的事情。
人们似乎都这样觉得，两个女人在一起亲热，
大半是某次心血来潮，或某种终究会过去的阶段。
只要好男人出现，她们会变回去的。
所以异性恋男人喜欢看这种场景，
并不觉得受到了什么威胁。
异性恋男人事实上促进了这些场景的出现，
所以很多情况下，两个女人在屏幕上亲热
算不上什么认真的剧情。
[1978年电影 《午夜特快》]
但如果你去电影院，看到男人之间的爱抚，
不只关于性，还表达出了深情，人们就接受不了。
人们认为男人应该是坚强而没有感情的。”
“好莱坞对于原剧本的修改经常让我不满，
电影经常抹掉剧本那些女同性恋因素，
我有时坐在电影院里忍不住想抗议。
这些角色确实是‘女同志’，但电影并没有这样表达。”
如果你母亲看到我们一起喝醉了，她会怎么想？
别去介意别人的想法了！
[1991年电影 《煎绿茄》]
我的意思是，你总是做好事。
当你作牧师的父亲生病的时候，你细心照顾他。
你照顾那么多教堂学校的孩子。
你会照顾好你妈妈的。
我知道，看来我还得嫁个我应该嫁的男人。
你要结婚了吗？
夏天一结束就要结了。
“这两个女人之间那份悸动的感情
并没有在电影中被公开地表达。”
我会想你的。
“就好象有人向我洒了一脸跳蚤。
我一直痒痒地，心想为什么他们不把事实给说出来。”
Daniel Melnick[曾做过电影公司的头]
“这一行业的每个人，拿的都比我们的父辈多，
而付出的努力又配不上所拿到的薪水，
所以人们一直害怕，
得到的这一切忽然被收回，
这就是为什么电影的角色是倾向保守的。
为什么美国的大富翁多是倾向保守的。
为什么大多数报纸是倾向保守的。”
“而公众却总是走在他们前面，
我是这么觉得的。
如果你能做好，打动人心，
你能抓住公众的心思，你就能大获成功。”
[1993年电影 《费城故事》]
“总有一部分电影公司持有坚决的愿望：
去创造令人喜爱的角色，
我在荧幕上的角色并没有太大的威胁性，
当我的角色走进房屋，或者一下出现时，
并不想让观众留下一个恐惧周围一切的印象。
所以，这个角色，一个患有艾滋病的同性恋，
并不是个提心吊胆的胆小鬼。
他可以有其他特点，但不需要提心吊胆。
你并不会对这个角色的存在，感到有什么威胁，
也许部分是因为Tom Hanks在扮演这个角色。”
-我的血液检查怎么了？
-在等结果。我建议你做个结肠检查，我们得看一看。
听上去不错。
等一下，为什么要这么做？
你是谁？
-你又是谁？....医生
-他是我的伴侣。
他有着我的所有病院记录，你可以和他说。
我是Klenstein医生。
你说得对，结肠检查不是非常好的选择。
但如果是恶性肿瘤引发的腹泻，
我们必须要好好的检查。
但也有可能只是寄生虫，或者感染。
也许是AZT（治疗HIV的药物）造成的不良反应。
都有可能，但最好是做结肠检查。
他不会做这个检查的，
这会打乱我们一切的安排。
我在尝试帮助你的伴侣。
-你不是他的直系亲属。
-我不是？
我有权把你赶出急症室，
医生，他只是很不安，他会道歉的。
不要替我道歉，好吗？
好吧，他不会道歉。
“我们的想法是：有一群观众想要看到
一个美国同性恋的故事。
想要看到一个染上艾滋的美国人的故事。
我们把自己当作观众，设想自己站在售票室前，
想着‘我要看什么电影好？
看关于外太空的超级间谍的故事？
看会说话的母牛的故事？
看一个患艾滋的律师的故事？或者看木偶表演？
恩，还是看艾滋病律师吧，这个有点与众不同。’”
“《费城故事》确实很棒，
但我并不觉得它证明了什么，
这是一个最终死去的同性恋英雄，
一个悲剧形象。
看来好莱坞和公众还是不能接受
一个活着的同性恋英雄。”
Ron Nyswaner[《费城故事》的编剧]
“我们当时想，如果我们的电影是面向这样的观众，
他们已经认为歧视艾滋病人是错误的，
或者面向那些已经认为歧视同性恋是错误的观众，
这电影反而会失败的。
如果编剧的想法和观众一样，
是写不出有深意的剧本的。”
“我们最后都会选择，
陪伴我们走完人生的爱人到底是谁，
至少看上去我们都在找。
就好象电影里Andy找到了Miguel，
Miguel找到了Andy。
当两人决意彼此相伴的时候，
一切对他们来说都是爱的证明。
这爱是由时光证明的，是恒久的，如同光速。
我想这是电影告诉我们的事。
爱是一样的，
不管在谁那里，‘爱’字都是一样写的。”
Harvey Fierstein[《火炬三部曲》主演/编剧]
“我们在学校里学到的一切东西
都是关于异性恋的生活。
看到的每一部电影都是关于异性恋的生活，
我必须要做‘翻译工作’。
我不得不把这种异性恋的生活‘翻译’
成自己的生活，而不是直接观看自己的生活。”
两星期纪念日快乐。
[1988年电影 《火炬三部曲》]
哦，Ed,你还记得
“这就是每当有人说，
‘你的电影不应该只拍给同性恋看，它应该面向所有人’
我回答‘随你怎么想，对我来说它就是同性恋的’
你可以看看它，然后把它‘翻译’成你自己的生活，
这次我不用作‘翻译’了，你来作。”
[1993年电影 《喜宴》]
[1992年电影 《夺魂》]
长久的沉默终于结束了。
[1991年电影 《毒药》]
新的声音出现了，公开而坦然。
[1994年电影 《钓鱼去》]
[1992年电影 《时光》]
人们开始讲述那些从来没有好好讲过的故事。
那些一直存在着的人们的故事。
[1991年电影 《爱德华二世》]
[1992年电影 《末路》]
我们是性解放运动的受害者。
上一代人是享乐够了，而我们全都被贴上标签了。
“电影是重要的也是危险的，
你知道，我们就象梦想的守护者，
你进了一家小小的黑黑的房间，就容易毫无防备。
[1992年电影 《哭泣游戏》]
你的所有观点都可能受到挑战和质疑。
[1991年电影《我私人的爱达华》]
你感受到平时感觉不到的东西。
[1983年电影《西尔克伍德》]
这可能鼓励你，去做你自己生活的主角。
[1994年电影 《沙漠妖姬》]
另一方面，它也很可能误导你，将你洗脑。”
[1991年电影 《沉默的羔羊》]
[1992年电影 《本能》]
“在那段有着严格检查制度的时期，
我不会想要讨论同性恋的正确形象，
只是想要讨论同性恋的真实形象，
想想这些真实生活中的英雄故事吧。
[1990年电影 《长期伴侣》]
同性恋们勇敢地承受放逐，
他们成长，相爱，最终生存了下来，
[1985年电影 《我的美丽洗衣店》]
他们也是真正的英雄。
[1983年电影《莉安娜》]
[1995年电影 《潇洒有情天》]
-你父母知道你是同性恋吗？
-当然。
我16岁的时候就告诉他们了。
[1986年电影 《离别秋波》]
16岁？
我在高中交了个男朋友。
他们吓坏了。
你知道，说了一大通陈词滥调。
“你怎么可以选择这样的生活呢，Peter？”
我回答，“嘿，是这种生活选择了我”。
我希望你穿上衣服，然后离开。
[1985年电影 《爱的甘露》]
-不，你不会这样做的。
-我会的。
不，你不会。
我不知道该做什么好了。
你可以先在门上挂上“请勿打扰”的牌子。
“好莱坞仍然面临某一些人的压力，
这些人害怕在电影中表达同性恋主题，
甚至只是提及同性恋，会将同性恋合理化。
是啊，他们当然害怕了。
因为这些电影告诉我们同性恋也是有血有肉的人。”
电影让我们哭也让我们笑，
我希望
电影能够让我们真正了解人性的多样性。
-这不公平，你爱过别人。
-只有一次。
你现在不见他了吧？
我正看着他。
我爱你。
我也爱你。
Subtitles downloaded from www.OpenSubtitles.org
Tommy, hit it up. Let's have it.
- May I cut in?
- Why, certainly.
Boys will be boys.
Not all girls are raving
bloody lesbians, you know.
That is a misfortune that
I am perfectly well aware of.
She says that I think more of you
than I do of her.
Well, you do, don't you?
Well, we won't go into that.
Go right ahead, boys.
Don't mind me.
But you're not a girl.
You're a guy.
- Why would a guy want to marry a guy?
- Security.
I think that the right woman
could reform you.
You know, I think the right woman
could reform you too.
These aren't my clothes.
Well, why are you
wearing these clothes?
Because I just went gay
all of a sudden!
In a hundred years of movies...
homosexuality has only rarely
been depicted on the screen.
When it did appear, it was there
as something to laugh at...
or something to pity...
or even something to fear.
These were fleeting images,
but they were unforgettable...
and they left a lasting legacy.
Hollywood,
that great maker of myths...
taught straight people
what to think about gay people...
and gay people what to think
about themselves.
No one escaped its influence.
Movies are part of my life...
part of everybody's life.
That's where we learn about life.
Watching Cary Grant taught me
how to behave with a woman...
how to get dressed at night, how to
go to a restaurant and order dinner.
They're our storytelling.
They're the fabric of our lives.
They show us what is glorious...
and tragic and
wonderful and funny...
about the day-to-day experiences
we all share.
When you're gay...
and don't see that reflected
in any way ever in the movies...
you began to feel that
something truly is wrong.
You feel invisible.
You feel like a ghost...
and a ghost that
nobody believes in.
There's this sense of isolation.
Join the club, man.
There's a whole group...
that is not represented.
We are pathetically starved
for images of ourselves...
so much so that a friend will call...
and say, "There's a movie you must see."
This happened to me.
"This movie you've got to see. There's
this incredible lesbian relationship.
There's this great love scene.
All right, they're vampires.
But you gotta see it.
It's great."
There are lots of needs for art.
The greatest one is the mirror...
of our own lives and our own existence.
That hunger I felt as a kid
looking for gay images...
was to not be alone.
My mother took me
to the silent movies...
in a spirit of
ostentatious condescension.
she said they were nothing like life...
and I must not believe them.
she was wrong.
Everyone who comes from England
to America and goes back...
says one thing first.
"It's more like the movies
than you'd ever dream."
And it is.
From the very beginning,
movies could rely on homosexuality...
as a surefire source of humor.
Your ideas about who you are
don't just come from inside you.
They come from the culture.
In this culture, they come from movies.
We learn from the movies what
it means to be a man or a woman...
what it means to have sexuality.
The movies did provide us
with some kind of history...
of how society
thought homosexuals were.
A very good example is a Chaplin film...
Behind the screen.
There's a moment where Chaplin
kisses someone who looks like a man.
He knows that it's a woman.
someone else comes along
and sees it...
and immediately starts swishing around
in the most overt effeminate way.
It's fascinating that those stereotypes
were so completely in place...
that a mainstream popular film
could assume...
that the audience would know
what this swishy mime was all about.
- Mr. Ernest!
- Ernest.
Dear Ernest!
Dear Lady Grayston.
Ernest, I'm so happy
you were able to come.
You must excuse my coming
in my town clothes...
but your chauffeur said there wasn't a
moment to lose, so I came just as I am.
Enter the sissy...
Hollywood's first
gay stock character.
The sissy made everyone feel more manly
or more womanly...
by occupying the space in between.
He didn't seem
to have a sexuality...
so Hollywood
allowed him to thrive.
They were sissies. They were
never addressed as homosexual.
It was a convention
that was totally accepted.
They were perceived as homosexuals
just subliminally.
This subject was not discussed...
privately, certainly not publicly.
It wasn't discussed, but you knew.
They were all very prissy...
these little skinny white men with
little mustaches who would go like this.
Stop. Stop. Girls, girls, girls!
Be careful of my hats.
We gotta get down on the stage.
I don't care.
I won't allow you to ruin them.
I told ya they were
too high and too wide.
Well, big woman.
I designed the costumes for the show,
not the doors for the theater.
I know that. If you had,
they'd have been done in lavender.
This is ripped. Who were you with?
strangler Lewis.
Catch as catch can, hmm?
If we could get the runs with this show
these dames get in their stockings...
I'd be able to make
the second payment on my kimono.
Here, Clarence.
Put that in the trunk.
And don't wear it.
Selfish.
They were a clich?
I don't care whether
they were a gay clich?or what...
I thought they were disgusting...
unfunny, had no business
being in it...
and I never understood
why people laughed.
It's the same thing when they had
the steppin' fetchits for the blacks.
I liked the sissy.
Is it used in negative ways?
Yeah, but...
my view has always been
visibility at any cost.
I'd rather have negative
than nothing.
That's just my particular view,
and also because I am a sissy.
And go dashing up and down the hall
In one movie you could
even find sissies table-hopping...
in Hollywood's first peek
at a gay bar.
If a sailor in pajamas I should see
I know he'll scare
the life out of me
And on a great big battleship
you, d like to be
Working as chambermaids
sissy characters in movies...
were always a joke.
There's no sin like being a woman.
When a man dresses as a woman,
the audience laughs.
When a woman dresses as a man,
nobody laughs.
They just thought
she looked wonderful.
I saw Marlene Deitrich in Morocco
when I was a teenager.
I just was flipping
the channels and saw her...
and decided to settle in
for an old movie.
There's the scene where...
she comes into a nightclub,
and she's just stunning...
in this tuxedo.
- May I have this?
- of course.
The camera lingers. I wasn't catching
this out of the side of the screen.
It's right in the center.
she has a romance with Gary Cooper
in this movie...
but that romance just went
right out the window for me.
I was, "Who was that woman?
What had happened?"
I start writing a whole other script
for what was really going on.
The thing worked for everybody
of every sex.
What's amazing...
I don't think they've done anything...
as delicious sexually
as that since.
They didn't pretend
it was anything but what it was.
she was doing it to turn on
both the woman and the man...
which appealed to everybody,
as it should.
It was so free.
Ebba! Come in!
Now don't dally, Your Majesty.
You have a busy day.
Morning, Ebba.
- What are you doing up so early?
- I couldn't sleep.
The movie Queen Christina was based
on the life of a real Swedish monarch...
and lesbian.
Hollywood changed the story, but
traces of the truth seemed to linger.
There are rumors that Your Majesty
is planning a foreign marriage?
They are baseless.
But, Your Majesty,
you cannot die an old maid!
I have no intention to, Chancellor.
I shall die a bachelor!
We hope that it will not
be necessary...
to close all
the motion picture houses...
because of some undesirable ones.
But that we will have cleaner...
and better motion pictures
so that they may all stay open.
What happened, of course, in the 20s
and 30s when they got very raunchy...
the Catholic Church and fundamentalist
Protestants came down hard.
It was a lot of pulpit stuff...
preaching about orgiastic aspects...
of what was happening on the screen.
The big change occurred when
the movie moguls got together.
"Let's save Hollywood.
We must get an outsider."
Preferably some politician...
who was above suspicion.
So they looked into the cabinet
of Warren G. Harding.
At that time, there were a number
of unindicted members of his cabinet.
They picked the Postmaster General,
Will Hays of Indiana...
who looked not unlike Mickey Mouse.
The code sets up
high standards of performance...
for motion picture producers.
It states the considerations which
good taste and community value...
make necessary in this universal form
of entertainment.
Will Hays would head the movies, first
voluntary effort at self-censorship.
The early Hays code was a token gesture,
seldom taken seriously.
But by 1934, the Catholic Church
had devised a scheme of its own.
The Legion of Decency...
not only rated movies as to content
but threatened massive boycotts.
Hollywood promised
to play by the rules.
The Hays code just
set up a series of rules...
that were inviolable.
Code director Joe Breen ran
Hollywood's censorship machinery...
for over two decades.
He was authorized to change words,
personalities and plots.
A novel about
a sexually-confused alcoholic...
became a movie about
an alcoholic with writer's block.
A novel about gay bashing and murder...
became a movie about
anti-semitism and murder.
our American people are a homely...
and wholesome crowd.
Cockeyed philosophies of life,
ugly sex situations...
cheap jokes and dirty dialogue
are not wanted.
Decent people don't like
this sort of stuff...
and it is our job to see to it
that they get none of it.
- Have you ever modeled before?
- No, I haven't.
I'm doing a study of
a young girl's head and shoulders.
You won't object to removing
your blouse, will you?
No, I guess not.
You can get ready behind that screen.
For all its efforts, the production code
didn't erase homosexuals from screens.
It just made them harder to find.
Now they had a new identity...
as cold-blooded villains.
I'm ready now.
I suppose you'll want these
pulled down, won't you?
Yes.
Why are you looking at me that way?
Won't I do?
Yes, you'll do very well indeed.
Do you like jewels, Lily?
This is very old
and very beautiful.
I'll show it to you.
I don't think I'll pose tonight.
I think I'll go, if you don't mind.
Please don't come any closer!
I didn't expect to see you,
Mrs. Danvers.
I noticed a window wasn't closed.
I came to see if I could fasten it.
Why did you say that?
I closed it before I left the room.
You opened it yourself, didn't you?
Rebecca is one of the movies
in which the word...
homosexuality or lesbianism
is never uttered...
but there's
this one scene that...
really stands out
for a gay audience.
That is, Rebecca is dead.
she was the beautiful woman...
who is mysteriously
not on the scene any longer.
Her former housekeeper,
Mrs. Danvers...
is obsessed with her,
even after her death.
This is where
I keep all her clothes.
You would like to see them,
wouldn't you?
Feel this.
It was a Christmas present
from Mr. DeWinter.
He was always giving her
expensive gifts, the whole year round.
I keep her underwear on this side.
They were made specially for her
by the nuns in the convent of St. Clair.
she opens the underwear drawer.
It's so sensuous.
Look. You can see
my hand through it.
The guys who ran that code
weren't rocket scientists.
They missed a lot of stuff.
If a director was subtle enough
and clever enough, they got around it.
What'll it cost
to be on the safe side?
Okay, go ahead.
- Gardenia.
- Quick, darling. In with him.
We know Peter Lorre's gay in The Maltese
Falcon even before we see him.
We're told there's a man outside...
wearing perfume... gardenia.
Then we also hear
some kind of funny...
slightly oriental, feminine music.
- You'll sit down, Mr. Cairo?
- Thank you, sir.
The original novel didn't mince words
about Peter Lorre's character.
It read, "This guy is queer."
May I offer condolences for
your partner's unfortunate death?
The movie could only hint...broadly.
See, Mr. Spade,
I'm trying to recover...
an ornament that,
shall we say, has been mislaid?
I thought and hoped
you could assist me.
That ornament is a statuette.
Black figure of a bird.
Leave it to Alfred Hitchcock to create
not one but two gay villains...
murderous lovers
based on real-life psychopaths...
Leopold and Loeb.
We knew that they were gay, yeah, sure.
Nobody said anything about it.
This was 1947.
Let's not forget that.
That was one of the points of the film.
Brandon, how did you feel?
- When?
- During it.
I don't know really.
I don't remember feeling
very much of anything...
until his body went limp...
and I knew it was over.
And then?
Then I felt
tremendously exhilarated.
How did you feel?
I don't think the censors
at that time realized...
that this was about gay people.
They didn't have a clue.
That's how it got by.
sometimes the censors turned a blind eye
to lesbians on the screen...
as long as they were kept
safely behind bars.
- Hi, Anne!
- Hello, Harper.
Since you went fancy working upstairs
for Benton, I kind of missed you.
This is Marie Allen.
Mrs. Benton says to put her in laundry.
Marie's gonna have a baby.
A baby, huh?
Why, you're just a kid yourself.
- So long, Marie.
- Good-bye, Anne. Thank you.
Let's you and me
get acquainted, honey.
You may be a number to the others,
but not to me.
Sit down in this chair.
It's kind of roomy.
There's supposed to be
a social message to all this.
"Isn't it terrible to go to prison,
to lose your femininity?
Isn't it terrible
for a woman to go hard?"
What's your name?
How'd you hurt your hand?
I'm a big girl, and this isn't
my first year away from home.
The name is Marie Allen.
If I said no to Kitty,
I'm sure not gonna say yes to you.
she's a cute trick.
In Young Man With a Horn,
we have one of my favorite...
lesbian glamour symbols.
Jo's interesting, isn't she?
so simple and uncomplicated.
Must be wonderful
to wake up in the morning...
and know which door
you're going to walk through.
She's so terribly normal.
She's a good singer too.
I like Lauren Bacall because
she gets up in the morning...
and she has no idea
what's going to happen to her next.
I'm dying to see
the rest of your sketches.
We'll have dinner out
and then go back to my place.
How nice of you to come
to the party, Richard.
This is my husband.
Miss Carson, I told you about her,
the girl who paints so well.
- How do you do?
- See you at 9:00 then, Amy.
- Fine.
It's been a wonderful party.
Those movies were a warning to ladies
to just watch it...
and get back to the kitchen
where God meant them to be.
What a swell combination we were.
You said you wanted experiences, Amy.
Well, here's one for you.
I'm leaving you.
I'd like to kill you.
You almost did.
You're a sick girl, Amy.
You'd better see a doctor.
I look back on the '50s now
and think that it was halcyon.
People were still being educated.
There wasn't a race war on.
The drug thing wasn't...
It seems like
a kind of paradise now.
But at the time
we were living through it...
we thought that
we were in a decade...
of such towering
dullness and stupidity.
I want to be proud of him.
That's why I had him
in the first place.
But he makes it so difficult for me.
My associates ask what he wants to be,
and I have to tell them that...
he hasn't made up his mind...
because I just won't tell them
he wants to be a folksinger.
The grief
of love endures
In '50s America masculinity ruled.
seeming gay was almost
as bad as being gay...
so a man had to watch
his every step.
Look, Tom, the way you walk...
I'm just trying to help you!
Nobody gave a damn about how
I walked till last week!
Forget it!
- Al?
- Yeah?
Tea and sympathy
is definitely about being homosexual.
I'm sorry. Tell me how I walk.
It's a film that's
about curing homosexuality...
and the signs of homosexuality
are effeminacy.
Well, then, you walk,
and let me watch you.
- I never noticed how you walk.
- okay.
Do it again.
- If you tell the guys about this...
- You think I would?
We know the Sal Mimeo
character is gay...
party because he has a picture
of Alan Ladd in his locker...
but also from his adoration
of the James Dean character.
You want to come home with me?
There's nobody home at my house.
Heck, I'm not tired. Are you?
See, I don't have
too many people I can talk to.
Who has?
People talk about whether
that was a homosexual relationship.
The intention wasn't that.
But any film is at the same time...
an expression of a writer...
and it's an offering to an audience
to create their own film.
Are you cold?
Rebel was about
tenderness, intimacy.
It was an attempt to widen
the permission to love...
when men were supposed
to be one way with each other.
- Can I keep it?
- Well, what do you think?
Here.
I think if I were writing
that script again today...
that I would be much more
specific about Plato.
I would let him be
an outcast because...
the gang thought
he was a faggot...
and let his isolation
come from that opinion.
- What do you guys want?
- You know what we want!
- We want your friend!
- Yeah, we got eyes for him.
The real rebel seems to me
the Sal Mineo character.
He's got something
to be rebellious about...
namely, being gay
in a homophobic society.
He, of course, has to be killed.
- Turn out the lights!
- Jim!
That's what happens to real rebels
in our society.
You got very good at
projecting subtext...
without saying a word about it.
The best example I lived through
was writing Ben-Hur.
Ben-Hur and Messala,
one Jewish, one Roman...
had known each other from youth.
They disagree over politics and hate
each other for the next three hours.
That isnt much to put
a whole three-hour movie on...
even something
as gorgeously junky as Ben-Hur.
The director of the movie,
William Wyler, said "What do you do?"
I said, "Let me try something."
Let's say these two guys were 15, 16
when they last saw each other.
They had been lovers,
and they're meeting again...
and the Roman wants to start it up.
Messala, played by Stephen Boyd,
wants to start it up again...
with Ben-Hur,
played by Charlton Heston.
Heaven knows why, but he does.
Anyway, he's Roman.
so Willie stared at me,
face gray.
I said' "Well'
I'll never use the word.
There will be nothing overt.
But it'll be perfectly clear
that Messala is in love with Ben-Hur...
Willie said, Gore, this is Ben-Hur.
A Tale of the Christ, I think
is the subtitle, he said vaguely.
Willie finally said, "Well, it's
certainly better than what we've got.
We'll try it...
After all these years.
Still close.
In every way.
He said, "You talked to anybody
about this?" And I said' "No."
He said, "You talk to Boyd..."
Messala.
"Don't say anything to Heston.
Chuck will fall apart.
I'll take care of him."
So Heston thinks he's doing
Francis X. Bushman in a silent version.
His head is constantly on high
like this and like this.
Stephen Boyd is
acting it to pieces.
There are looks that he gives him
that are just so clear.
I said I'd come back.
I never thought you would.
I'm so glad.
- Look at you.
You've come back a tribune.
When I heard that news,
I drank a toast to you.
We'll drink another now.
Once I had a secret love
That lived within
The heart of me
Hollywood had learned to write
movies between the lines.
some members of the audience
had learned to watch them that way.
Gosh a-mighty!
You're the prettiest thing
I ever seen.
Never knowed a woman
could look like that.
- How do you hold that dress up there?
- Please!
It's amazing how
if you're a gay audience...
and you're accustomed
to crumbs...
how you will watch an entire movie
just to see somebody wear an outfit...
that you think means
that they're a homosexual.
The whole movie can be a dud...
but you're just sitting there...
waiting for Joan Crawford
to put on her black cowboy shirt again.
I'm going to kill you.
I know...
if I don't kill you first.
Gay audiences were desperate
to find something.
I think all minority audiences
watch movies with hope.
They hope they will see
what they want to see.
That's why nobody
really sees the same movie.
Let's give 'em a hand over here.
That's a good-looking gun you were
about to use back there. Can I see it?
Maybe you'd like to see mine.
Nice. Awful nice.
Monty Clift and John Ireland
knew what they were doing.
I think that's why
the scene is funny...
'cause of their delight
in playing the sexuality of the gun.
There are only two things
more beautiful than a good gun.
A Swiss watch
or a woman from anywhere.
You ever had a good Swiss watch?
Go ahead. Try it.
Hey, that's very good.
Hey, that's good too.
Go on. Keep it going.
Most expressions of homosexuality
in most of movies are indirect.
What's interesting is that
that, of course...
is what it what like to express
homosexuality in life.
That we could only express
ourselves indirectly...
just as people on the screen could
only express themselves indirectly.
There's a sense in which
the characters are in the closet...
the movie's in the closet,
and we're in the closet.
Now I shout it
From the highest hills
Even told the golden daffodils
At last
My heart's
An open door
And my secret love's
No secret
Anymore
one, two, three, four
There were films
even in the '50s that got away...
with an amazing amount
of at least gay subtext.
You can't keep...
gay life or behavior out of the movies.
It's like keeping it out of life
in general.
It pops up often in somewhat hidden
or somewhat coded ways.
In the film
of Gentlemen Prefer Blondes...
there's a gym full of bodybuilders
who have no interest in Jane Russell.
He don't have to be Hercules
Don't anyone know about birds and bees
Ain't there anyone here for love
sweet love
Ain't there anyone
Here for
Love
Doubles? Anyone?
Court's free!
Two out of three?
Anyone?
Doesn't anyone want to play?
In the '50s and '60s,
especially in sex comedies...
there were often characters
who could be read as gay...
whether they were
the Tony Randall roles...
or the boss of
the decorating establishment.
And here.
This isn't bad either.
What colors that floor?
Lilac.
Lilac? Leonard, who has
a lilac floor in their kitchen?
I have.
Oh, well, Leonard, everyone
isn't as artistic as you are.
We have to sell this wax to
average, ordinary, everyday people.
Them!
In Hollywood for years and years...
there was what was called the DF movie.
All the Doris Day movies
were DF movies.
It was delayed fuck because they
couldn't sleep together until married.
No sex before marriage.
That was the law of Hollywood.
What a marvelous-looking man.
I wonder if he's single.
I don't know how long
I can get away with this act...
but she's sure worth a try.
Rock had a screening room in his house.
He liked to assemble his houseguests
and show his old movies.
Most of the guys I knew liked
to see the old Doris Day films.
one of the reasons we laughed at them...
was that there was
a real gay in-joke occurring...
in almost all
of those light comedies...
because at some point or another
the character Rock Hudson played...
posed as gay in order
to get a woman into bed.
Tell me about your job.
It must be very excitin' workin' with
all them colors and fabrics and all.
It was tremendously ironic.
Here was a gay man
impersonating a straight man...
impersonating a gay man.
Ain't these tasty?
Wonder if I could get the recipe?
sure would like to surprise my ma
when I go back home.
We're all half man, half woman.
We come from those two cells,
you know?
so when I put together Josephine
in some Like It Hot...
I thought of Grace Kelly...
thought of my mother...
and a little bit of Eve Arden.
- My name is Josephine.
- I'm Daphne.
I thought my top lip was a little thin'
so every time I stopped talking I'd...
- Men!
- You don't have to worry about that.
We wouldn't be caught dead with men.
Rough, hairy beasts with eight hands!
That kind of sexuality of ours
which overlaps...
some like it hard.
some like it soft.
That kind of waving in there
is in that movie, just delicately.
Osgood, I'm gonna level with ya.
We can't get married at all!
Why not?
Well, in the first place,
I'm not a natural blond.
Doesn't matter.
I smoke. I smoke all the time.
I don't care.
I have a terrible past. For three years
I've lived with a saxophone player.
I forgive you.
I can never have children.
We can adopt some.
You don't understand, Osgood.
I'm a man!
Well, nobody's perfect.
When the subject turned serious
and actual sex was suggested...
out came the blue pencil,
the scissors and the scene.
"Antoninus, Sicilian, age 26...
singer of songs."
For whom did you practice
this wondrous talent?
For the children of my master,
whom I also taught the classics.
Classics, indeed.
What position have we, I wonder,
for a boy of such varied gifts?
You shall be my body servant.
Instruct him.
All of you, come with me.
The first time you see Antoninus
is there in the lineup...
when he says,
"I want him for my body servant."
That's the only indication.
Body servant. What does that mean?
He says body servant. The next thing you
know we're in the tub. I'm washing him.
In here with it.
There's some chat between us,
and then finally he says to me...
''Antoninus, do you like snails?"
I said, "Yeah, I do."
"What about oysters?"
I said, "Well, I don't think so."
Do you consider the eating
of oysters to be moral...
and the eating of snails
to be immoral?
No, Master.
of course not.
It is all a matter of taste,
isn't it?
Yes, Master.
And taste is not
the same as appetite...
and, therefore,
not a question of morals, is it?
You can see even
in that long shot I've...
I'm kind of getting an idea
what he's trying to say to me.
I said, "Yes, Master."
He says, "Well,
I like both oysters and snails."
He realizes that
he's going to be asked...
to do something
he's not prepared to do.
I liked Antoninus
for that, you know?
Take me out to dinner first.
Give me a little good time.
Don't throw me in the tub
and drop the soap.
My taste includes
both snails and oysters.
They cut that scene out.
I have never seen such a time
in my life with censorship.
You started drinkin' with your friend
skipper's death. That's the truth.
They cut and cut Cat on a Hot Tin Roof.
There was no way Brick could have had
any kind of sexual desire for his buddy.
What are you suggesting?
- Nothin' but...
- But what? Say what's on your mind.
say it!
- Why are you so excited?
- Go ahead! say it!
- What are you shouting like that for?
- skipper and I were friends.
- Can you understand that?
- Gooper and Mae said that skipper was...
skipper is the only thing
I got left to believe in!
- You are dragging it through the gutter!
- Now, just a minute...
You are making it
shameful and filthy, you...
It was clear to anybody on the
right wavelength what you were doing.
You just couldn't use the word.
I met this head-on in a movie
called suddenly, Last summer...
from a Tennessee Williams play.
You know why I was doing it.
I told you.
I was procuring for him.
Sebastian was lonely, Doctor.
The Legion of Decency...
headed by this
shark-like Jesuit priest...
I must have had
five meetings with him.
"You can't say this.
You can't say that."
By the time we started to cut it,
it was making no sense at all.
Sebastian only needed you
while you were still useful.
- Useful?
- I mean, young, able to attract.
she's babbling again,
babbling and lying.
He left her home
because she had lost her...
- Because you stole him!
- Lost her attraction.
What would attraction have
to do with a son and a mother?
- I'll tell you...
- Is there no way to stop these lies?
Yes! Have my brain cut!
It was like working under the Kremlin,
like writing for Pravda.
You did learn how to write between the
lines or photograph between the lines.
You do it with a look, or
there'd be a take on Hepburn's face...
as Elizabeth Taylor
would be telling her...
getting closer and
closer to the truth...
which the Legion of Decency
wouldn't dare let us say.
- We were decoys.
- Decoys?
For Sebastian.
He used us as bait.
When she was no longer able to lure the
better fish into the net, he let her go.
Bait for what?
What were the better fish?
We procured for him.
Did Sebastian like boys or not?
Well, the fact that he's eaten up
at the end by...
Admittedly, Tennessee occasionally went
over the top with his dramatic effects.
When he tried to escape
from those streets...
down those little side streets
between the buildings...
they came from everywhere...
so the only way was up.
Sebastian Venable was
the perfect homosexual for his times...
one without a face or a voice.
since he lives as a monster,
he must die as one...
in a scene reminiscent
of an early horror classic.
I don't know how he still ran.
He never ran.
But he ran and he ran
and he ran!
He never reached the end!
Never!
They overtook him.
He screamed just once.
I... I... Then I... Then I...
Help!
So Suddenly, Last summer opens, and the
New York Times is going to destroy...
this degenerate film,
the work of degenerates.
so you've got a review from
Bosley Crowther that said...
"If you like incest, rape,
sodomy, cannibalism, degeneracy...
this is the movie for you,
this sickening picture."
Everybody in the country went to see it.
That review made the movie.
A taut...
tense drama of the most...
of the most untalked-about subject.
While Hollywood
remained reticent...
British films began
to tackle homosexuality head-on...
with a major star like Dirk Bogarde
as the screen's first gay hero.
I want to know the truth.
I want to know why he hanged himself.
He was being blackmailed.
- That's why he stole?
- Yes.
someone found out he was a homosexual
and blackmailed him?
That's it.
It takes two to make
a reason for blackmail.
Were you the other man?
Were you?
There is a scene in the film in which...
he is quite explicit about...
wanting to have sex
with another man.
That's an extraordinary statement
for a star of that magnitude...
in a popular entertainment movie
to make in 1961.
All right, you want to know.
I shall tell you.
You won't be content
until you know, will you?
Till you've ripped it out of me!
I stopped seeing him
because I wanted him.
Do you understand?
Because I wanted him!
Back in Hollywood, the production code
had gradually been whittled away.
Moviemakers, fed up with restrictions,
set out to smash the last taboo.
Homosexuality was finally
being talked about on the screen...
but only as something
that nice people didnt talk about.
We've seen things too.
- What things?
- Bad things. I can't tell you.
You're annoying me very much.
If you have anything to say, say it.
I mean, I can't say it out loud.
I've got to whisper it.
- Why must you whisper it?
- I don't know. I've just got to.
At the time we made the picture...
there were not real discussions
about homosexuality.
Do you know what you're saying?
It was about a child, s accusations.
It could have been about anything.
stop the car, John!
so none of us
were really aware.
We might have been the forerunners,
but we weren't really...
because we didn't do
the picture right.
We were in the mind-set...
of not understanding...
what we were basically doing.
You've got to know!
I've got to tell you!
I can't keep it
to myself any longer.
I'm guilty!
You're guilty of nothing!
These days there would be a tremendous
outcry, as well there should be.
Why would Martha break down and say,
"What's wrong with me?
I'm so polluted.
I've ruined you."
she would fight.
she would fight for
her budding preference.
When you look at it,
to have Martha play that scene...
and no one questioned
what that meant...
or what the alternatives could
have been underneath the dialogue...
It's mind boggling.
We were unaware.
Don't you see?
I can't stand to have you touch me.
I can't stand
to have you look at me.
It's all my fault!
I've ruined your life,
and I've ruined my own.
I swear I didn't know it!
I didn't mean it!
oh, I feel so damn sick and dirty!
I can't stand it anymore!
The profundity of this subject...
was not in the lexicon
of our rehearsal period even.
Audrey and I
never talked about this.
Isnt that amazing?
Truly amazing.
The loathing she feels...
How sick she is with herself...
It still makes me cry when I see that.
I think, why am I crying?
Why does this still get to me?
This is just an old silly movie.
People don't feel this way anymore.
But I don't think that's true. I think
people do feel that way today still.
There's part of me,
despite all my little signs...
"Happy. Proud. Well-adjusted.
Bisexual. Queer. Kinky."
No matter how many posters
I hold up saying...
"I'm a big pervert,
and I'm so happy about it..."
there's this part of me that's,
like, how could I be this way?
He said to tell you before
you go on with the Lefflngwell matter...
you ought to remember
what happened in Hawaii.
Then he hung up.
What happened in Hawaii, Brig?
What was the voice like?
It was crawly. He made it sound like
he knew some kind of nasty secret.
I've been on the front pages
the past few days.
Bound to get some crackpot calls.
Just hang up if you get anymore.
I saw Advise and Consent when
I was in my senior year in high school.
Very much a virgin. I didn't
actually have sex with anybody...
until I was 25 years old...
so everything was theoretical
at that point.
All I saw was a life that
might lie down the road for me.
Let me hear a voice
A secret voice
A voice that will say
senator Brigham Anderson,
who's being blackmailed...
goes to check out
this former lover at a bar.
It was my first glimpse
into what I imagined...
organized gay life to be,
and it was very, very scary...
because it suggested people who have
to remain hidden in the shadows.
Well, come on in.
Don't just stand there.
Don't run off.
Ray! You're with me!
Brig?
- Wait a moment, Brig.
- Taxi!
- Let me explain. Brig, wait a moment.
I needed money, Brig!
Well, you wouldn't see me.
I kept calling. I was drunk.
Drive, will ya? Drive!
I felt that something dreadful
was going to happen to me...
something that I wouldn't
be able to turn back...
once I'd actually had sex
with another man...
and that the end of that road
would be suicide.
I got that impression
from the movies.
Is that Brig?
What's the matter?
He's dead.
Brig?
In his office.
He cut his throat.
Oliver saw you.
You were with Dove all afternoon.
You know, lying to me, Haley...
oh, well, perhaps maturity
will change all that.
What do you think
I'll mature into?
You?
I want to know what's going on
between you and that boy.
Are you in love with
that Texas dirt farmer?
He's more than that.
It's gone quite far already, hasn't it?
You'd like to make him happy.
Make all his dreams come true.
- Perhaps even get married.
- Yes, even get married.
All right,
I'll be sorry to lose you.
But if you think the world
is your oyster, go ahead and take it.
How do you think the boy is going to
feel when he finds out what you are...
what you've been?
- He'll forgive me.
- All right, go to him.
After all, a girl like you
has so much to offer a man.
A knife to cut his heart out.
- I'll change!
- Of course you'll change!
But haven't you said that so many times
before? But go on and tell him.
Tell him about the days and nights
of Haley Gerard.
Tell him about the mud
you've rolled in for years!
Well, tell him!
Growing up in that period in the '60s...
all we had were images of unhappy...
suicidal, desperate gay people.
The thought of turning...
of turning involuntarily...
into one of them...
frightened me and
made me sick with anger.
I went down there.
I had heard about the waterfront.
People giggle
and make jokes about it.
I had had only
two experiences before...
once in college,
once in the army.
I thought I'd gotten it
out of my life, but I hadn't.
I looked at them.
Was this what I was like?
Oh, my God.
Twisted faces, outcasts...
lives lived in shadows,
always prey to a million dangers.
People don't realize
what we go through.
I was raised in a family
that would not even admit...
that there was such a thing
as a homosexual in this world...
and here I was...
and I couldn't do
anything about it.
I couldn't stop!
These images magnify...
the sadness...
the hatred of us...
the prediction that
we will not find love.
How come you never got married?
You're not bad-looking.
Features are good.
Nice legs...
ankles.
But you never had a man?
I think that's really your problem.
I think the fate of gay characters...
in American literature, plays, films...
is the same as the fate of all
characters who are sexually free.
Haley?
Get Jo out of here!
You must pay.
You must suffer.
If you're a woman who commits adultery,
you're only put out in the storm.
If you're a woman who has another woman,
you'd better go hang yourself.
It's a question of degree, and if you're
gay you have to do real penance... die.
I knew you were gay
the moment you walked into the bar.
How could you know?
We know each other.
something about the way you walked.
something about the eyes.
What's the matter with you?
Let go of me!
I'll call the police!
Let go!
- Don't.
- Operator?
Don't do that!
You bitch!
By now,
the pattern was clear...
characters
of questionable sexuality...
would meet with a nasty end
in the last reel.
Feed your faces and keep your traps shut
if you don't want to...
Kill her. Kill her! Kill her!
Oh, Martha.
When the time comes,
you won't have the guts.
It's not always like
it happens in plays.
Not all faggots bump themselves off
at the end of the story.
- One, two. one, two.
- Oh, Christ.
Single, single, dip.
- Wait a minute!
- One, two, three.
It's the geriatrics Rockettes.
Finally, it happened.
Hollywood made a movie in which gay men
took a hard look at their own lives.
It's the sensational Menstruations!
And, in a refreshing twist...
they all survived.
The great thing about seeing
The Boys in the Band...
I hadn't come out yet...
and what it did for me
was present gay men...
as having this incredible sense
of camaraderie...
this sense of belonging to a group
which I, d never really felt before.
Forget your troubles
Come on, get happy
You better chase
all your cares away
What's more boring than a queen
doing a Judy Garland imitation?
A queen doing
a Bette Davis imitation.
I knew a lot of people...
like those people.
I would say that probably
all nine of them...
are split-off pieces of myself.
What I am, Michael, is a 32-year-old,
ugly, pockmarked Jew fairy...
and if it takes me a while
to pull myself together...
if I smoke some grass before I get up
the nerve to show myself to the world...
it's nobody's goddamn business
but my own.
And how are you this evening?
They were miserable and bitchy.
If I was wrong...
it was definitely
a reflection of what was...
wrong in my head.
But that's the way
I saw things then.
You're a sad and pathetic man.
You're a homosexual,
and you don't want to be.
But there's nothing you can do
to change it.
Not all your prayers
to your God.
Not all the analysis you can buy in
all the years you've got left to live.
You may very well one day
be able to know a heterosexual life...
if you want it
desperately enough...
if you pursue it with the fervor
with which you annihilate.
But you'll always be
homosexual as well.
Always, Michael.
Always...
until the day you die.
Friends...
thanks for the nifty party.
I think that
the self-deprecating humor...
was borne out of a...
low self-esteem, if you will...
from a sense of what the times
told you about yourself.
Homosexuality was still classified
as a mental illness.
You went into a gay bar,
you were liable to be arrested...
or the place be raided.
I've been in those situations.
There were still
not just attitudes...
there were laws against...
one's being...
the core of one's being.
If we could just not
hate ourselves so much.
That's it, you know.
If we could just learn
not to hate ourselves...
quite so very much.
The first film...
that really celebrated homosexuality,
as far as I was concerned, was Cabaret.
For me, it embodied the very life I was
beginning to live in San Francisco...
one in which there was no real onus
placed on homosexuality.
Doesn't my body
drive you wild with desire?
Well, doesn't it?
Lt's a very nice body.
Do you really think so,
darling?
It does have
a certain kind of style.
I mean, look,
it's very flat here...
not much hips...
and...
here.
It's a little early in the day
for this sort of thing.
Maybe you just don't
sleep with girls.
oh.
You don't.
Listen, we're practically
living together...
so if you only like boys
I wouldn't dream of pestering you.
Do you sleep with girls,
or don't you?
You don't ask questions
like that.
I do.
The boy was homosexual...
and it seemed rational, reasonable.
I mean, that's what the story was.
There was no fuss with anybody.
None at all.
Oh, screw Maximillian!
I do.
so do I.
So, things changed...
more quickly
than you might imagine.
- And who are you?
- I'm Bernstein.
- You're Jewish?
- No, darling, I'm gay.
I don't care how you feel.
You're a great dancer.
You're not bad yourself.
I think it was easier...
for the powers that be...
to show a black rather than
a white character as a homosexual.
Why? I don't understand that.
But I do understand it...
just like it's more easy
for us to have...
the sitcoms, situation comedies,
on television...
and not the serious dramas
about our lives.
But a lot of things
can be said through comedy.
Would you please get out of my face...
you sorry-looking faggot?
Who you callin' sorry-lookin'?
Can't y'all see
that she ain't funny?
She's just another poor example...
of how the system
destroys our men.
Honey, I am more man than you'll ever be
and more woman than you'll ever get.
shit!
But there was a downside
to the new gay visibility.
The threat of retaliation
could be waiting just down the road.
This is the first image I remember...
having of gays in a movie I saw.
It was the hitchhikers
that were picked up in vanishing Point.
Pardon me. Could you tell us
which direction you're headed?
I'm going to Frisco.
Oh, well, that's perfect.
Thank you.
one of the guys was carrying a purse.
They wore very tight, pinched clothes.
He had a lascivious look
on his face.
Why are you laughing?
I'm not laughing.
Yes, you are.
It's because you think
we're queers, isn't it?
This is a stickup.
stickup?
Why are you laughing, Mary?
We all howled, because all you saw was
the car speeding at 60 miles per hour...
then screeching to a stop
and the two guys were thrown out.
We thought that was great..." Remember
when the two homos got thrown out?"
We thought that was amazing.
There it was, almost the image
of what a homosexual was.
Bitch.
To be gay not only meant wearing pinched
clothes with this look on your face...
but you also carried a purse.
I've had the experience
of being in a theater...
and really enjoying a movie...
and then suddenly, out of nowhere...
comes some kind of
pseudo-homosexual character...
who is the villain, the killer,
or is killed...
and the audience
bursts into applause.
I was with friends and we were
watching Freebie and the Bean.
There's this killer transvestite...
who does sort of
a murderous ballet.
And of course, triumphantly,
our hero pulls out a gun...
and blows five million holes
through the murderous transvestite...
and the audience
burst into applause.
There were two things
happening there.
People were applauding
the death of the villain...
but they were also applauding
the death of a homosexual.
You know you're watching a heterosexual
movie when you see a Hollywood movie...
but you don't... you're still not
quite ready for being insulted.
Do you know, at this moment...
I have sunk as low as I can go.
I was wrong.
Are you gonna tell me you're a fag?
I don't think I can handle it.
I'm not a fag.
I'm a werewolf.
I never hear the word "nigger" used...
unless it's by two black people...
as a form of affection...
or by a...
totally bigoted southern sheriff.
You know,
the blubbering stereotype.
To point out his ignorance,
he would use that term. You see?
"Faggot" is not used in that way.
"Faggot" is used by just anyone
talking to anyone else.
Hey, doesn't this cafeteria
have a "no fags allowed" rule?
Hey, killer.
Why are you on your knees?
You queer or somethin'?
I know what you've been after,
you goddamn faggot.
You must be creamin'
all over your faggot self.
After all this, you won't have to hang
out with that faggot Caesar anymore.
Unhappy, faggot?
You're a faggot,
a dirty queer.
- You a queer?
- Hell no, sir!
What's the matter?
You goin' faggot?
You turnin' fag on me?
- Oh, you're a tough faggot, ain't you?
- What do you faggots want?
You hear me,
you fuckin' faggots?
- Fuck you, faggot.
- Fuck you, queer.
- Who is this faggot?
- You bald-headed, flatfoot faggot.
You become either inured to it
or conditioned to accept it...
and it becomes the attitude...
the prevailing attitude.
It becomes the way people
perceive gay people.
When Hollywood finally acknowledged
the burgeoning gay scene...
it came up with a grisly thriller...
set in the world of leather bars.
- How big are you?
- Party size.
- What are you into?
- I go anywhere.
- I don't do anything.
- That's cool.
Hips or lips?
I did have an experience
with the movie Cruising.
Not about seeing the movie,
but being the victim of someone who had.
My lover and I were gay-bashed by
young men who worked in a movie theater.
They threatened us...
they chased us out of the theater,
into the street...
and as I was escaping from one of them,
he said to me...
"If you saw the movie Cruising,
you know what you deserve."
Who's here?
I'm here.
You're here.
Now I'm afraid.
Homosexuals in movies
had changed...
from victims to victimizers.
show it.
Lift up the sweater.
Please. Please. Please.
You made me do that.
stop the movie Cruising!
Gays fight back!
one movie boldly showed homosexuality...
as an act of love, not violence.
so Hollywood had to warn the public.
This was 1982.
There hadn't been any gay characters...
in leading roles.
okay, the truth is, I have gotten
into a lot of different scenes.
I'm a writer.
I have to open myself up
to new things...
expand my horizons.
Why don't you just say it?
I'm gay.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
It was very hard to cast.
The men were hard to cast...
because every one of their advisors...
both Harry Hamlin
and Michael Ontkean...
told them not to play
someone who was gay...
that it would destroy
their careers.
There was the general perception...
at least in the early '80s...
I don't know what it's like now...
that Hollywood was a cowboy town.
A straight cowboy town.
I am sure that inside of me there is
the same homophobia that we all share.
If I see a guy
who's playing a gay role...
I'll question it and say,
"Wow, is he gay?"
Why I do that, I don't know.
Then I'll stop and say, "That's silly.
You've been there, you've done that."
The question is,
why do we care?
I mean, who cares?
I'll do that.
The ownership of the studio
changed hands...
and a new person came in
who was not from the film world...
nor the intellectual world...
nor the world
of letters and arts...
and I had the unpleasant task...
of running in the screening room
for this man...
and his lovely wife
and daughters...
the rough cut of the film.
None of my colleagues would be there.
They were all afraid.
I was there by myself,
in the back.
He was sitting up front
in the small screening room.
He was squirming all during the movie.
He just couldn't sit still.
And at the part in the movie...
where the two men
embrace and kiss...
he jumped up and said...
"You made a goddamn faggot movie"...
and stalked out.
The day it opened,
I happened to be in Miami.
We sat down, the movie started...
and as the movie progressed...
you sensed the audience
growing more and more uncomfortable...
with what was going on the screen.
It kept escalating.
When they had the first kiss, it seemed
there was an explosion in the theater.
People panicked.
There was pandemonium.
People started storming up the aisles.
At that point, I just left.
Mainstream people...
dislike homosexuality...
because they can't help concentrating...
on what homosexual men do
to one another.
And when you contemplate
what people do...
you think of yourself doing it...
and they don't like that.
That's the famous joke...
"I don't like peas,
and I'm glad I don't...
because if I liked them I'd eat them,
and I hate them."
There was a time when men were free
to express tenderness on the screen.
But as the world grew more aware
of homosexuality...
male-to-male affection would be seen
as an incriminating act.
A kiss would become an assault...
or an ugly accusation.
I'll show you what you're gonna be.
What you are.
I'll kill you for that!
Americans, perhaps,
are more scared of their sexuality.
They're prepared to show violence
of all kinds...
but when it comes to sexuality...
America is both self-righteous...
and tries to bury it
as if it didn't exist, which is silly.
Are you all right?
We had quite an argument
about the kiss.
The screenwriter felt the whole thing
should be in silhouetted long shot.
I said, "No way.
It should just happen."
And that's what we did.
There's a difference in how audiences
look at two men getting it on...
and two women getting it on.
There's a comfort
with female nudity...
and female girlishness
and girly bonding...
that it can be sexy and it can be
completely palatable, even erotic.
Women don't find it threatening...
and men find it either completely
unthreatening or titillating.
straight men are more uncomfortable
with two men making love...
because somehow
that means you're weak...
and people equate weakness
with male sensuality toward other men...
not realizing that
that's a ridiculous theory.
That's why people say,
"I'm a man"...
like being a man is based on
who you happening to be boning that day.
In The Color Purple,
Celie has fallen in love with Shug.
They're two women
who love each other.
This intimacy...
is not about sex.
I think it's much deeper.
Let's keep goin'.
What do you mean?
It's much easier for audiences to accept
2 women being affectionate than 2 men.
That's a big, big taboo.
You sure?
Hit it.
But when I put the kiss in
at the end of Thelma and Louise...
that gave people pause.
I told Geena.
I didnt tell anybody else.
They were beyond sexuality. It was love.
If you're about to go off a cliff,
I don't think you're gonna make a pass.
To me, it was a declaration of...
that they were at a point where they
were finishing each other's sentences...
and they were there for each other
in the tradition of Butch Cassidy...
except that they didnt get shot down.
Go.
Wouldn't that have been great
if Butch and Sundance...
Well, then they would've had
more reason to shoot them, I suppose...
if Butch and the Sundance Kid
had kissed at the end.
But they did what guys do
in movies...
They got their guns out, because
they couldn't get their dicks out.
They got their guns out and went down
with their guns. That's what boys do.
Are you making a pass at me,
Mrs. Blaylock?
Miriam.
Not that I'm aware of, Sarah.
Originally, the script was a Playboy
version of them getting together.
It had a lot to do...
with lingerie and posing.
There was no real scene.
And so I said that
I really thought that what was sexy...
would be the first moment
the people touch.
so I came up with the little scene
where she spills something on herself...
she gives her something,
they touch that way, they have a kiss...
and then you go into all of the curtains
blowing over their bodies stuff.
The other thing was,
they felt I should be really drunk.
That was their way of taking away
her choice, in a sense.
I insisted that
that not be that way...
that certainly you wouldn't have to
get drunk to bed Catherine Deneuve...
I don't care what your sexual history
to that point had been.
It was much more interesting
if she went voluntarily.
I don't think,
for better or worse...
that women are taken
very seriously in this area.
I think the feeling is,
if two women are together...
then it's probably experimental
or some kind of phase...
and if the right guy came along
that would all change.
so it's something that straight men
can watch and not be threatened by.
And straight men are the ones that are
propelling the industry forward...
so I don't think
it's taken that seriously.
I suppose when you go to the movies
and you see men being affectionate...
besides the sex, the affection itself...
is just too much.
Guys are supposed to be
strong and unfeeling.
I get so angry...
about what Hollywood will do
with an original story or script...
to get rid of
the lesbian element...
that I feel like standing up
in the theater and just shouting.
These characters are dykes,
and this movie isnt saying so.
What's your mother gonna say
when she sees us both drunk?
stop worrying about what people think.
I mean, you've always
done the right thing.
You took care of your daddy,
the preacher, when he took sick.
You take care of all the kids
over at the church school.
You're gonna take care of your mama.
I know, and I'm gonna marry
the man I'm supposed to.
You're gettin' married?
As soon as the summer's over.
The passion that these two women
feel for each other...
was not presented in an open way
in the movie.
I'm gonna miss you.
It's like somebody's
just powdered me with fleas.
The entire time I'm being irritated
that they're not telling the truth.
Everybody in the business...
we all get paid more than we should,
more than our fathers ever made.
There's always the fear that...
they're gonna take it away,
so we'd better be...
And that's why most people
in those roles are conservative.
Most people who run big businesses
in America are conservative.
Most newspaper chains are run
by people who are conservative.
The public is always ahead of us
about what they're ready for.
I think.
And if you do it well,
if you pierce the heart truth...
of what the public is feeling
and thinking, you have a hit.
There is this constant desire
on the part of the studios...
to make characters likable.
My screen persona
is pretty much non threatening.
I have never been one to strike fear
into anybody's heart...
when I enter a room
or first appear on screen.
Because of it, then, this idea
of a gay man with AlDS is not scary.
It's something else,
but it doesn't have to be scary.
You don't have to be threatened
by this man's presence in it...
part of it because little Tommy Hanks
is playing the role.
- What about my blood work?
- We're waiting.
I wanna prep you for a colonoscopy.
We want to take a look inside.
sounds delightful.
Wait a minute.
Why do you need to do this?
Who are you?
Who are you, Doctor...
- This is my partner.
- Yeah?
He keeps records of all my hospital
visits. It's nothing personal.
I'm Dr. Klenstein.
Listen, you're right. A colonoscopy
is not a pleasant procedure.
But if the Ks is causing the diarrhea,
we've got to know about that right away.
But it could be parasites,
an infection.
A reaction to the AZT.
All of these are possibilities, but
we've got to perform the colonoscopy.
He's not going through
some painful procedure...
until we cancel out
everything else.
I'm trying to help your partner.
- You're not in his immediate family.
- I'm not?
I could have you
removed from the ER.
Look, he's upset.
He's sorry.
Don't apologize for me, okay?
Okay, he's not sorry.
The idea that there had to be
an audience that wanted to see...
stories about
being gay in America...
who wanted to see stories about
a guy who has Al Ds in America...
is this almost backward understanding
of how it works...
when you're standing in front of the
box office in your local dodecaplex...
and you have a choice between...
"What movie should we see?
We can see the movie about super spies
from outer space, a cow who talks...
the lawyer who has Al Ds
or the big puppet show.
Well, I guess the lawyer with AlDS.
That's the one that's most different."
Philadelphia was terrific,
but I don't think it proves anything.
It's about a gay hero who dies...
and who is a tragic figure.
It remains to be seen whether
Hollywood and the general public...
will embrace a film
with a gay hero who lives.
We felt that we would fail...
if our movie played to people...
who already think that discrimination
against people with Al Ds is wrong...
or people who already believe...
that people shouldn't discriminate
against homosexuals.
If our movie only played to people
who thought just like we do...
we would have done nothing
very significant.
We all end up choosing who we're gonna
be in love with the rest of our lives.
It seems that's what
we're all searching for.
Andy found Miguel,
Miguel found Andy.
That's a love that is born
out of everything that goes into...
two people deciding to be
with each other.
It's forged through time.
It's a constant... the speed of light.
That's what the movie is saying.
It is all the same. Love is spelled
with the same four letters.
Readings in school were heterosexual.
Every movie I saw was heterosexual...
and I had to do this translation.
I had to translate it to my life,
rather than seeing my life.
Happy two-week anniversary.
Oh, Ed, you remembered.
Which is why,
when people say to me...
"Your work is not really gay work,
it's universal"...
I say, "Up yours. It's gay.
That you can take it and translate it
for your own life is very nice...
but at last I don't have to
do the translating... you do."
The long silence
is finally ending.
New voices have emerged.
open and unapologetic.
They tell stories
that have never been told...
about people who have always been there.
We're victims of the sexual revolution.
The previous generation had all the fun,
and we get to pick up the fucking tab.
Movies are important
and they're dangerous...
because it's, you know,
we're the keeper of the dreams.
You go into a little, dark room...
and become incredibly vulnerable.
All your perspectives can be challenged.
You feel things you normally couldnt.
It can encourage you...
to be the protagonist in your own life.
on the other hand,
it can completely misshape you.
There's been an incredible era
of censorship...
of, I wouldn't say positive images
of gays and lesbians.
I would say real images
Think of all the heroic
stories that are real.
Here gay and lesbian people
have lived...
braving ostracism, loving, surviving.
There are so many real heroic stories.
- Your parents know you're gay?
- Sure.
Told 'em when I was 16.
sixteen?
I had a boyfriend in high school.
They freaked.
You know, the usual bullshit.
"How could you choose
this kind of lifestyle, Peter?"
I said, "Hey, it chose me."
I want you to get dressed and leave.
- No, you don't.
- Yes, I do.
No, you don't.
I wouldn't know what to do.
You can start by putting
the "Do Not Disturb" sign on the door.
Hollywood still runs scared
from people...
who feel that the very mention
of homosexuality...
the very display of it,
in some form, on the screen...
legitimizes the subject.
Well, of course it does. It shows
that homosexuals are human beings.
The movies could be making us
laugh a lot more and cry a lot more...
if they would actually acknowledge
the true diversity of humanity.
- Not fair. You've been in love a bunch.
- Just once, really.
Now he's gone, right?
He's right here.
I love you.
I love you too.
Best watched using Open Subtitles MKV Player